<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plain discovery of the unrighteous judge and false accuser wherein is soberly ... brought to light ... the spirit of that pamphlet, intituled, The leper cleansed ... by Richard Ballamy ... as also, a clear vindication of ... Anabaptists ... / by Robert Steed and Abraham Cheare ...</title>
            <author>Steed, Robert, of Dartmouth.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93844</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5376B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223912</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875785</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875785</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152411</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93844)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152411)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2296:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plain discovery of the unrighteous judge and false accuser wherein is soberly ... brought to light ... the spirit of that pamphlet, intituled, The leper cleansed ... by Richard Ballamy ... as also, a clear vindication of ... Anabaptists ... / by Robert Steed and Abraham Cheare ...</title>
                  <author>Steed, Robert, of Dartmouth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 78+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Mortlock ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, lacks all after p. 78. Best copy available for photographing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anabaptists --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152411:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Plain Diſcovery OF The UNRIGHTEOUS JUDGE And FALSE ACCUSER.</p>
            <p>Wherein is ſoberly, and in the fear of the Lord brought to light, and tendered to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of the Upright in Heart, the Spirit of that Pamphlet, intituled, <hi>The LEPER Cleanſed:</hi> Publiſhed by <hi>Richard Ballamy</hi> of <hi>Tiverton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo, A clear Vindication of the PRINCIPLES and PRACTICES of the people by him charged, from thoſe Reproaches therein heaped upon them, under the notion of ANABAPTISTS.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by <hi>Robert Steed:</hi> and <hi>Abraham Cheare,</hi> Servants of Chriſt, among his deſpiſed People.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 18.17.</hi>
               </bibl> He that is firſt in his own cauſe, ſeemeth juſt; but his neighbour cometh and ſearcheth him.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Job 13.7.</hi>
               </bibl> Wilt thou ſpeak wickedly for God, and talk deceitfully for him?</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Job 31.35, 36, 37.</hi>
               </bibl> — And that mine adverſary had written a book; ſurely I would take it upon my ſhoulder, and binde it as a crown to me: I would declare unto him the number of my ſteps; as a pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e would I go neer unto him.</q>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Henry Mortlock,</hi> at the Phoenix in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, neer the little North-door. 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152411:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152411:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not without a multitude of diſadvantages on our hand, that the enſuing Defence cometh into open view, ariſing, not only from the Reproach that is on us, and the weakneſs that is in us of ſaying any thing worthy of the cauſe, which in the main we deſire to plead; but withal (to ſay no worſe) from the infirmity of the age we live in: the generality of men being led into the affecting and diſlike of things, rather by tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and upon the credit of ſuch as they reverence, then upon a right judgement of matters in their own evidence. Yet are we not diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged from ſending this Teſtimony forth, though it hath neither Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, nor Approbation; but only Truth to be its Shield and Buckler: being clear in this, that it was not an Affectation to appear in publick, that hath led us forth to this Undertaking; but a neceſſity of vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating the Churches of Chriſt that we walk withal, from ſuch notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſlanders: as alſo, of delivering the Readers of that Pamphlet from the manifeſt abuſe it puts upon them, expoſing them to a temptation of giving credit to very many untruths and miſ-repreſentations of things, and therein to a diſguſt againſt the Way, and all that walk therein: which is the main deſign thereof.</p>
            <p>The Book was indeed by many thought unworthy of an Anſwer, for a time; but ſeeing it grew into repute by the countenance of ſome that are accounted men of worth, who ſcattered it abroad as an undoubted Evidence of Truth; we have thought good to give men a warning at preſent againſt ſuch artifices to deceive, that for the future they may be the more cautious of giving credit to invectives of this nature, which will not be much our care hereafter, to make Replies unto; as having it in our hearts to expect many ſuch trials from men of perverſe minds, apoſtatizing from the Truth in this hour of temptation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152411:3"/>
            <p>That the preſenting this to thee, comes to our lot who dwell at ſome diſtance from the place where theſe affairs were tranſacted, is occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned from our obſervation, how that the Reproach of this, falls heavier upon us in the Countries, then it doth on them in that Town, where the advantages of informing the Enquirers, and clearing the accuſed, are at hand: by reaſon whereof, that people being leſs ſenſible, have been the leſs careful of performing this ſervice, which might ſeem more properly appertaining unto them.</p>
            <p>Yet neither doth our diſtance of place render us uncapable of giving thee the true ſtate of things, in that our ſelves were eye and ear-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to the Proceedings of that Congregation in the two principal matters of fact he inſiſteth on, <hi>(viz.)</hi> with <hi>William Facy,</hi> and this <hi>Richard Bellamy;</hi> and for the other Occurrences, have taken all poſſible care to obtain ſuch a perfect account of things in the naked truth of them, as might render us capable of giving forth the Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive with all exactneſs.</p>
            <p>In the whole, however we had in our eye the Readers accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therefore endeavoured to be as brief as poſſible, in matters that may be ſo expreſſed; yet may it not be reaſonable to think, we can clear our ſelves from ſuch an heap of ſlanders, in as few words as he may caſt them on us; eſpecially, we have been enforced to be ſomewhat large in giving our underſtanding about what he lays down as grounds from Scripture, convincing him of Infants right to Baptiſm, which he offers as a main hinge on which he turned from us; and thence loads us with the common name of Infamy, that we paſs under among the ſons of men. Our Method is to follow our Accuſer ſtep by ſtep; wherein we repeat his words: and have willingly omitted nothing that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves an Anſwer, although it be againſt our ſelves: in the whole, being deſirous to approve our ſelves to him that ſearcheth the hearts: with him we leave the undertaking, to diſpoſe of it and us, and at his pleaſure: to him be Glory for ever.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 8. line 4. for <hi>Act.</hi> 2.34. read 39. page 9. line 49. for <hi>hating,</hi> read <hi>ſuiting.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152411:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A plain Diſcovery of the Unrighteous Judge, and falſe Accuſer.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>To all that love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in ſincerity, whom theſe may concern:</hi> Greet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Precious and Beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not our purpoſe to entertain yee with the Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the manner of our receiving the truths of Chriſt in which we ſtand, or of the preparations of Spirit, the Lord hath given in order to this work and by the help of this attire to allure your pious minds to our Cauſe and Perſons. Theſe vails have ſomtimes (it may be) obtained their ends, but being grown the common vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zour of every il-favored cauſe; we judge them not only impertinent to the matter in queſtion, but alſo unfit for us to publiſh of our ſelves; and no leſs unmeet to be impoſed on you whom we write unto as ignorant and ſimple; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as ſuch who can diſcern the things that differ in their own qualities.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard Bellamy,</hi> ſince he was caſt out of Comunion with us at <hi>Tiverton,</hi> (or whoever he be perſonated by him) hath printed his book againſt us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Called, <hi>The Leper Cleanſed.</hi> The title page tels you, of what the book is comprehenſive. Therein amongſt ſeverall laudable matters ſpoken of himſelf, he pretends to lay open the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts,</hi> and their unchriſtian wayes, and wiles to deceive; and ſeemeth deſirous to be thought a perſon able to make great diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and conqueſts, as having been througly verſed in the Doctrine and Practiſes of the whole body of that party by his nigh two yeers converſe with them in ſociety amongſt our Brethren in <hi>Tiverton.</hi> But all theſe terrible flouriſhes notwithſtanding, we herewith tender this man and his writings againſt us to your examination, and the true ſtate of our Doctrine, Way, and Practiſe, as it ſtands accuſed and judged by him. And if indeed we be convicted for cunning de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers, lyers in wait, hypocrites, enemies to Godlineſs, enemies to Magiſtracy and Miniſtery, as he hath informed the world, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152411:4"/>leave us, as he hath perſwaded you: But if theſe appear to be the unrighteous accuſations of a perſon puffed up, at beſt, with the heat of his own paſſions, then take heed and beware of that ſpirit which hath acted this man, and led him aſide according to the pride of his own heart, to play both the unrighteous Judge, and falſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer, againſt the way of God wherein we ſtand.</p>
            <p>Friends, We intend not in this defence to juſtify any evil perſon, or matter for our advantage; we are aſſured we have in hand, a cauſe of God that needeth not, ſave to be ſtated in its own ſimplicity: wherein we ſhall endeavour to be faithfull with you, being made willing by the grace of God to ſtand and fall with it. The perſons of men we ſhall not care to overvalue, or preſume to detract, but as men ſtand approved or diſapproved of the truth to give them their due: and particularly for this our Judge and Accuſer, we ſhall caſt behind us the filth of his invectives without retaliation; his impertinencies and abſurdities, as much as may be, we ſhall paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with ſilence, that what may be found in him to bear upon the mayn cauſe, may be dealt withal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It may ſeem ſtrange to all that know me, to ſee me in print: and if any that ſee me thus appear, judge that it is my mayn buſineſs to vindicate my ſelf, they are miſtaken; I am partly driven to this by the irregular proceedings of thoſe who have judged me at an offender, and yet would not give me liberty to ſpeak for my ſelf: ſo that I am enforced to ſpeak this way, or to juſtify them by my ſilence: but that which moſt of all prevails with me, is, Firſt to give glory to God-in acknowledging his mercy, who hath opened my eyes, and ſhewed me the error of my way.</hi> 2. <hi>I judge it my duty to labor to undeceive all the ſimple and plain hearted.</hi> 3. <hi>I think it as neceſſary to diſcover the hypocriſie of ſome that ly in wait to deceive, and by cunning inſinuations and pretences to draw aſide many ſouls, to their own loſs, if not to their deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not much that we ſhould think needfull to ſpeak to this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph: only whereas he begins, <hi>It may ſeem ſtrange to all that know me, to ſee me in print;</hi> In this the Accuſer ſpeaketh right, for we have ground to judge, he doth but perſonate the contrivance of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who have judged me as an offender, and yet would not give
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152411:4"/>me liberty to ſpeak for my ſelf.</hi> We ſhall hereafter meet our Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer in this his falſe allegation in its due place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I think it as neceſſary to diſcover the hypocriſie of ſome that ly in wait to deceive, &amp;c.</hi> Whom he intends under theſe expreſſions; as hypocrites, lyers in wait, &amp;c. he manifeſts in the title page; how well he proves us to be ſuch, appeareth by the ſequele of his book, where we ſhall have full opportunity to examine it. He proceeds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is notoriouſly known to all the Inhabitants of</hi> Tyverton, <hi>that I was deeply ingaged in that way, which is commonly known by the name of</hi> Anabaptiſts; <hi>yea ſo far as that I thought I was bound to oppoſe all that diſſented from that way as being antichriſtian: &amp; ſo zealous was I to promote that intereſt, that I forſook my rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and left my fathers houſe, not caring for any ſociety, but ſuch as were for that way; refuſing to joyn in prayer with ſuch as differed from me in that, though otherwiſe godly: thus I continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the ſpace of nigh two yeers, but at laſt God was pleaſed to cauſe me to reflect upon my ſelf and wayes, and by ſome ſpeciall providences (of which by and by I ſhall give an accompt) he made me willing to ſtand upon the ways and ſee, and enquire for the way of the Lord; for untill this time I was ſo filled with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice againſt the publick Miniſtery, that I refuſed all confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences and debates, with any (though offered with never ſo much mildneſs) concerning the way in which I was; or if I did at any time admit of any, it was to defend, and not to examine it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this raſh and uneven walking while under this profeſſion, that this man makes diſcovery of himſelf in (for we ſhould not have judged it worth the while to have given ſuch a character of him) it eaſily appeareth to have ſprung from the youthfull vanity and lightneſs of his own ſpirit, not from any priaciple owned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us; nor was the obſervation of it any comfort to us, in that he was ſeverall times reproved for ſundry of thoſe very things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But now God having put ſome check upon my ſpirit, I began to lay things in the balance; and obſerving another people in this place, walking under Ordinances, and joyned with the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Miniſtery: ſuch thoughts as theſe would come in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152411:5"/>We ſay we are in the way of God and they ſay they are in the way of God: may not I all this while be miſtaken? Though I often oppoſed ſuch thoughts as theſe, yet they returned upon me by my obſervation, for I could not but take notice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that thoſe I walked withall, were looſer, both in their Principles and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, then thoſe I diſſented from.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then I began to lay things in the balance, &amp;c.</hi> Thoſe unſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy revolutions of thoughts, always learning, never coming to the acknowledgment of the truth; argue a minde unſtable as water and therefore cannot excell. <hi>I could not but take notice that thoſe I walked with, were looſer both in their Principles and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes then thoſe I diſſented from.</hi> We ſhall not in this place inſiſt on the weakneſs of the Argument, urged from the practiſes of ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to the error of their profeſſion. But to the generall charge, we ſay: That, if to ſtate the everlaſting Covenant, made and given by the Lord himſelf for the redemption of ſinners, and the efficacy of the Miniſtration thereof upon the free grace of God in Chriſt alone; and ſo ſtated, to miniſter the ſame, for the calling and gathering of the elect, the true ſeed in that Covenant given unto Chriſt, for the bringing them into viſible communion with Chriſt their head, and each with other: If to require a proof of the truth of this work be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore admiſſion into ſuch viſible communion and fellowſhip, with an pen profeſſion upon ſuch admiſſion to take up the croſs of Chriſt, and follow him, in doing and ſuffering his whole will, as himſelf requireth:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24. <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.26.</note> If to adminiſter ſuch Goſpel. Ordinances, as import the peculiar priviledges of the children and family of the Son of God, to perſons ſo approved, and no others: If to acknowledge and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the everlaſting Kingdom and Prieſthood of Jeſus Chriſt, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for, governing and perfecting his people, although a feeble flock; and therefore ſet at nought by them that are full and at eaſe: If while theſe principles and the like unto them, are in our eye, the mark we contend to reach unto (yet through the infirmity of our fleſh, finding our ſelves to our grief often beneath them) by the grace of God in his Ordinances, in bearing one anothers burdens, in admonition and exhortation with patience, whiles there is hope, and other ſpirituall proceedings, as the cauſe requireth; our manifold weakneſſes notwithſtanding, ſuch indulgence and grace we obtain with and from our God, that not only ſupport is miniſtred, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152411:5"/>(to the praiſe of his admired goodneſs be it ſaid) a progreſs is made among us from faith to faith: and this further token of his preſence we find among us: That uſually the moſt carnall, worldly, and unruly, are ſooneſt offended: but the ſober and humble hearted rejoyce with us. If theſe principles and practiſes, and the juſt conſequences attending them, commonly avowed by us, be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer then what the accuſer doth imbrace, and in his own perſon fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, the day of tryal wil make evident.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I found them ſlight in their thoughts of the Sabbath, and that they obſerved that day rather out of policy, then out of conſcience; not ſo much to ſanctifie the name of God, as to keep their hearers from attending the publick Miniſtery. They ſpake ſlightly of thoſe that walked ſtrictly and cloſely with God in duty, ſaying, that all the Religion of ſuch lay in duties but theirs was ſpiritual. I further obſerved that their families were without prayer generally their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren without inſtruction: and ſurely their conſtant neglect of duties in their families, made me grow very careleſs of mine in private. The conſideration of theſe things made me begin to enquire, whether this were the truth I profeſſed: from henceforth I reſolved to conſider what was objected againſt the way I was in, and to weigh the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments I had ſlighted, becauſe I ſaw many ſerious godly people did live in the profeſſion and practiſe of that which I oppoſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I found them ſlight in their thoughts of the Sabbath, &amp;c.</hi> What wormwood and gall hath he mingled to us in this deſperate and bold accuſation and judgment, it being full well known to all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers, that both in preaching, printing and practiſe, all the Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed congregations with whom we have communion in <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> do hold out a conſtant profeſſion, that in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Lord, we do hold our ſelves bound to keep the firſt day of the week, called the Lords day, holy to the Lord; and that the right celebration of this day conſiſteth in a ſpiritual communion with God, our own ſouls, and each with other in all goſpel-Ordinances, and other Chriſtian offices, of goodneſs and mercy to man and beaſt, as opportunity and Chriſtian prudence ſhall require. And this yong man wel knoweth, that this very congregation in <hi>Tiverton</hi> procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with a member as worthy of juſt cenſure, only for that his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, though without his knowledge, took a cloth upon this day out
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152411:6"/>of the rack where it was on drying; and moreover, himſelf was preſent when the Church appointed it as their judgment to meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether conſtantly about ſix of the clock in the morning, to the end that the day might be ſpent more intirely for the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They ſpeak ſlightly of thoſe that walked ſtrictly and cloſely with God in duties ſaying, that all the Religion of ſuch lay in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; bus theirs was ſpiritual.</hi> That there is a Phariſaical ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in poliſhing the outward-man by the traditions and inventions of men, and not of Chriſt; and a formal ſtrictneſs in the letter of a command, and both theſe deſperate enemies to the Goſpel of Chriſt, we affirme; but we loath, abhor, and deteſt, the application of theſe expreſſions, to the flighting of any duties, or exerciſes of godlineſs, or any perſons that in faith and a good conſcience, walk cloſely with God in them. That our ſelves might be built up, and be help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful each to build up other in the faithful exerciſe thereof without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction, hath been one main motive to draw us into the union and communion in which by the grace of God we ſtand, and is a part of that promiſe, which we through the Lords aſſiſtance (the God in Covenant with us) doe declare and undertake when we receive the right-hand of viſible fellowſhip together. As for the ground of this mans report in this particular, after the moſt diligent ſearch that could be made, we can finde out no juſt colour he hath for ſuch an accuſation, but that himſelf hath uſed the like expreſſions of ſome, as hypocrites and formaliſts, &amp;c. whom he now clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth unto: for which he was then faithfully reproved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Their families without prayer generally their children with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out inſtruction,</hi> &amp;c. What ſhall we reply to this bold man? the Lord knoweth we condemn, abhor and deteſt the guilt of this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, we faithfully exhort unto theſe Chriſtian duties, we reprove their neglect; and are in a readineſs to paſs publick cenſures upon the careleſs and wilfull tranſgreſſours of them, as perſons offending againſt plain precepts: The Lord knoweth we long and labour to have our houſes as churches of Chriſt, and our children in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion with all gravity, brought up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord; yet being jealous that ſeveral in Tiverton, and elſwhere, may not have been ſo careful in the performance of their duty in theſe things, as the law of the Lord requireth of them, we ſhall take occaſion, even from the reproach caſt upon us by the accuſer, to make a more ſtrict enquiry after all neglects of that kinde, truſting
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152411:6"/>the Lord will help us to beare yet a more effectual teſtimony againſt them, and help them and us unto a more thorow reformation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Becauſe I ſaw many ſerious godly people did live in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and practice of that which I oppoſed.</hi> We acknowledg this paſſage to have more reſemblance of grace in it, then moſt we can finde in all the book beſides. As for his toſſing and running from place to place upon matter of diſputes, and one while railing on this party, and then as fiercely reviling others, it is the common badg of the drunken ſpirit of this perverſe generation; but to pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the paths of the truly Godly upon well-digeſted and clear evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of the grace of God dwelling in their hearts, we cannot but commend, and put a due eſtimate upon: and we know that this very conſideration, hath been an introductive to a farther work of God, which hath not left ſome precious ſoules till they have taken up the viſible profeſſion of the Goſpel in which we ſtand. But let us beware that while we be tender to the Godly, we prove not cruel to Chriſt and to our own ſoules: the godly in all ages have been liable to ſaid miſtakes, and ſtiffly perſiſted in them, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they wanted not ſuch as have admoniſhed them of their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages: we can hardly be ſtrangers to this truth, while the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and the pulpits in the three nations, breath out ſuch ſharp con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions among our oppoſites themſelves, in ſundry points of great moment; and therefore let us follow the godly as they follow Chriſt, and no farther; and withal, take heed of making out a judgment while we are prejudiced with perſonal infirmities, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled, with wordly advantages or diſadvantages, but draw our ſelves and the matter in queſtion, into a naked ſimplicity before the Lord, to receive the pure impreſſions of Scripture-authority, as the ſupream judg of all controverſies, and no other. But mark the condition of the perſon, our judg and accuſer, before and ſince his defection, as his own pen hath painted him forth, that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his pretenſions of ſeeking and finding God, you will finde the man not ſo much in the joy and love of a ſpirit bettered by his change, as in the old gall of a deadly bitterneſs from firſt to laſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And upon ſerious inquiring into the word, and earneſt ſeeking of God, it pleaſed the Lord to ſatisfie me in the truth, and in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular touching theſe two controverted truths. (1.) That the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace ſtands now in force to the children of beleevers under
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152411:7"/>the Goſpel. (2.) That this is a ſufficient ground by Gods appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment why the children of believers ſhould be baptized. This is evident from many Scriptures in the New Teſtament, which the Anabaptiſts have endeavoured often to obſcure. I ſhall onely mention one which was uſeful to me, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.34. The promiſe is to you, and to your children. The Anabaptiſts have laboured to darken this truth by perſwading the world to believe that chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren have no right to the promiſe till they are actually called, which they would infer from the laſt clauſe of the fore mentioned Text. But by conſidering, I ſaw their miſtake in the Text <hi>[call]</hi> hath no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to children, but to them afar off.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We account it not our concernment, nor worth our while, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Reader, with what might be truely ſaid to diſcover the falſhood of the accuſers plauſible inſinuation, by what direct meanes, and with what mature conſideration he digeſted thoſe grounds of ſatisfaction: but letting him paſs with his deſired ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, ſhall only crave the exerciſe of Chriſtian patience while we follow him, laying down in plainneſs our perſwaſions about the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals by him hinted at in this point of Baptiſme; he firſt gives you two propoſitions as the ground of his ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, that the Covenant of grace ſtands now in force to the children of believers under the Goſpel. Secondly, that this is a ſufficient ground by Gods appointment why they ſhould be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed.</hi> Many miſtakes uſually perplex the point in queſtion for want of a right underſtanding of the termes made uſe of: which inconvenience we ſhall endeavour to remove out of the way, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we goe farther: and the terme or expreſſion that comes firſt to hand to be explained is <hi>[the Covenant of Grace.]</hi> This terme is applyed to ſignifie,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Covenant of Grace in its own nature, ſingly, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally conſidered.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It's applied to ſingifie the manner of its adminiſtration, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to divine inſtitution.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt ſignification the Covenant of Grace ſignifieth. That great myſtery of the mercy of God in Chriſt, wherein the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath eſtabliſhed Jeſus Chriſt his Son, the head of all things, and given unto him a bleſſed ſeed of the Sons of Men, to be by him, and with him heires of the glorious inheritance of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152411:7"/>grace of God, and the bleſſed conſequences thereof, againſt all poſſibilities of miſcarriage, according to his eternal purpoſe. This Covenant was by the Lord himſelf firſt publiſhed to man in Paradice, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>I will put enmity between thee and the woman, and between thy ſeed and her ſeed: it ſhall bruiſe thy head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his heele.</hi> This Covenant is ſpoken by the Prophet <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 2.7. <hi>I will declare the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, the Lord hath ſaid unto me; Thou art my Son, this day have 1 begotten thee.</hi> Verſ. 8. <hi>Aske of me, and I ſhall give thee the heathen for thins inheritance, and the utmoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion.</hi> Verſ. 9. <hi>Thou ſhalt break them mith a rod of iron, thou ſhalt daſh them in pieces as a potters veſſel.</hi> This Covenant, is it which <hi>Iſaiah</hi> publiſheth and preacheth, <hi>Chap.</hi> 42. and 49. and elſwere frequently. This Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant God calls his everlaſting Covenant, being ſtill one and the ſame immutable from everlaſting to everlaſting. This Covenant was it which at ſundry times, and after divers manners, under di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſignes, figures, and types, by promiſes and prophecies was renewed and ratified with the bleſſed Patriarches, <hi>Abel, Seth, Enoch, Noah, Sem, Melchiſedeck,</hi> and with the Fathers <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> with <hi>Moſes,</hi> with <hi>David</hi> the king, and with the Prophets, before the comming of Chriſt: and it is the ſame Covenant, which openly and plainly was brough: to light, and revealed in all the myſteries of it by <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> the Lord Jeſus, and his Apoſtles, which ſtill continueth to be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in the Church, and ſhall continue without change to the worlds end. This Covenant hath one Spiritual Father, which is Chriſt, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 9.6. <hi>The mighty Ged, the everlaſting Father;</hi> and one ſpiritual ſeed, <hi>Pſal,</hi> 22.30. <hi>A ſeed ſhall ſerve him, it ſhall be accounted to the Lord for a Generation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Covenant of grace as it ſignifieth the manner of adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, according to divine appointment, may be thus deſcribed.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <note place="margin">The Covenant miniſtring.</note> It doth contain the whole and every part of that inſtituted worſhip, whereby God doth ordinarily bring about, the purpoſes of the everlaſting Covenant, that is, to ſet Chriſt upon his throne, and to gather to him the ſeed given him by his Father: And the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace under this acceptation is not one and the ſame al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, but hath paſſed under many great alterations and changes: the Lord hating his ordinances and appointmens, to the perſons,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152411:8"/>ſeaſons, and workes, which he had to doe, as it ſeemed good to his heavenly wiſdom: and therefore all the force and authority of the Covenant of grace, conſidered under this head, to wit, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the adminiſtration of it, dependeth intirely upon the law of its inſtitution, and is in force as that law directeth, and not otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>And the Covenant of grace in this ſence ſtands diſtinguiſhed in Scripture, under two known heads, reſpecting two ſeaſons, the ſeaſon before the aſcention of the Son of God, and the ſeaſon which followed after.</p>
            <p>The adminiſtration of the Covenant of grace,
<note place="margin">The miniſtring before Chriſt.</note> before the coming of the Son of God, paſſed under very great alterations and changes, for the firſt two thouſand years from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Abraham,</hi> the ordinances and forme of worſhip then in practiſe, and other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſional figures, having reſpect unto the myſtery of the everlaſting Covenant, and the choſen and rejected ſeeds therein conſidered, was a miniſtry dignified, with as eminent and glorious ſaints, as any the book of God recordeth: and although this miniſtry were alſo for the nature of it, the ſame with the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and proportioned to it, and afterward fell in with it, yet in all this long track of time, there was no diſtinguiſhing ordinance to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred to infants of believers, or any known doctrine to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, notwithſtanding the far-fetcht notions, which ſome have wandered after, to finde it out from that paſſage of the Sons of God and daughters of men, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.2. Which very probably was found in the family of holy <hi>Seth,</hi> in that time of univerſal cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of all man-kinde. Nor in that other of the ſaving of <hi>Noah,</hi> and his family, in the Arke; neither of which nor any other thing, was, or was deemed to be an ordinance eſtabliſhed in the Church, to be adminiſtred in infancy.</p>
            <p>True it is, at circumciſion it began, and by the law of <hi>Moſes</hi> circumciſion was taken in with the other inſtitutions which went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, and there it received its full enſtalment, and became the head-ordinance of the Levitical miniſtry. This adminiſtration of the Covenant of grace is uſually called in Scripture the old Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, or the firſt Covenant. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.7. <hi>For if that firſt Covenant had been faultleſſe,</hi> &amp;c. Ver. 13. <hi>In that he ſaith a new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, he hath made the firſt old.</hi> It is alſo uſually called the law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13, 14, <hi>For the promiſe that he ſhould be the heir of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152411:8"/>the world, was not to Abraham, or to his ſeed, through the law, but through the righteouſneſs of faith: for if they which are of the law,</hi> (to wit, the people of the old Covenant) <hi>be heirs, faith is made void.</hi> (to wit, the people of the new Covenant,) And <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.1. <hi>The law having a ſhadow of good things to come, and not the very image of the things,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.21. Ye that deſire to <hi>be under the law, doe ye not hear the law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Covenant, while it ſtood, although it were very glorious, yet the Spirit of God never exalted it in dignity above the degree of an Handmaid, appointed for the time being to miniſter to the everlaſting Covenant, and then to be utterly caſt out of the Church, together with her ſeed according to the fleſh, whom the Apoſtle calleth ſervants, and not ſons, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.7. All which we have prophetically, yet plainly and fully inſtanced in the family of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hans,</hi> under the type of the Goſpel-Church, under the perſons of <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael, Gen.</hi> 21.10, 11, 12. <hi>Caſt out this bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, and her ſen; for the ſon of this bond woman ſhall not be heir with my ſon, with Iſaac,</hi> &amp;c. The myſtery of this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the Apoſtle unvaileth at large, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.22,—31. Where he ſheweth that the two women, verſ. 24. under an allegory, are the two Covenants, the bondage Covenant, and the free Covenant, verſ. 25, 26. that is, the law and the Goſpel; and that the <hi>Iſaacs</hi> were the true ſeed of the Goſpel-adminiſtration, ver ſ. 28. called the children of the promiſe: and ſaith the Apoſtle, ſuch was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and all the Churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi> to whom he wrote, verſ. 31. Not borne after the fleſh as was <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> verſ. 23. but borne where there were no poſſibilities of nature, to bring forth a ſeed: even by the power of God, and ſpirit of adoption, verſ. 5, 6, 7. By a mother which in the other reſpect was altogether barren and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. verſ. 27. <hi>Rejoyce thou barren that beareſt not,</hi> &amp;c. that is, ſhee was in no ſuch mariage-Covenant, whereby children ſhould be brought forth unto her, as were the children of the former mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage-Covenant; but in that reſpect being left abſolutely deſtitute, ſhould yet have many more children, then that Covenant had which brought forth children by fleſhly generation.</p>
            <p>Again, this old adminiſtration, the Spirit of God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.5. Termed <hi>a ſervice unto the example and ſhadow of heavenly things.</hi> And Chap. 9. vers 9. <hi>a figure for the time then preſent.</hi> And in Chap. 7. v. 19. and cha. 10. v. 1. <hi>That it made nothing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152411:9"/>perfect.</hi> And that it was by the Lord Jeſus blotted out as an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing of ordinances, that was againſt us, which was contrary to us, and took it out of the way, nailing it to his Croſs, <hi>Col.</hi> 2, 24. There ended that Covenant; there expired the law, the force and authority upon which that adminiſtration ſtood. And there was the propheſie, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.10. of caſting out the ſeed according to the fleſh (never more to claime a priviledge upon that account) ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely accompliſhed and fulfilled. And thenceforth the children of the promiſe are counted for the ſeed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.8.</p>
            <p>Two hard ſhifts are made uſe of by ſome to avoid the evidence of theſe, and the like ſcriptures againſt infaint-baptiſme, which might be alleged to the ſame effect.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1</label> they ſay, that what hath been alledged from <hi>Gen.</hi> 24. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. Tendeth only to prove, that the legal Covenant and carnal ſeed, as it ſtood priviledged by that Covenant, was to give way to the free Goſpel-Covenant.</p>
            <p>To this we ſay,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rep. </seg>1</label> That the Covenant of the law, and the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> in the letter of circumciſion, had with them an eminent renovation, and ratification of the everlaſting co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; yet were both of one and the ſame nature, authority, and uſe, <hi>John</hi> 7.23. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.5. Although not given together; as neither were the ordinances of ſacrificing; and all alike ſignified, and ſerved unto the ſame heavenly myſtery of the grace of God in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>We cloſe with them herein,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and crave no more from theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures then the total aboliſhing of the legal covenant, with all its apputtenances, of which circumciſion was a chief, as hath been proved.</p>
            <p>We ſay that the excluſion of the ſeed,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> according to the fleſh, upon the account of the excluſion of that covenant, excludes the ſeed according to the fleſh for ever, becauſe it can claime a ſtanding by no other right.</p>
            <p>It is alſo ſuggeſted,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> that the Scriptures alledged unto the point of the two covenants, and the two ſeeds in them reſpectively priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, is not to be underſtood of any others intended by the ſeed of the free woman, then of real or inviſible ſaints, and not of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſubjects of the Goſpel Church.</p>
            <p>To which we ſay,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rep. </seg>
               </label> That if the Spirit of God hath made uſe of theſe diſcoveries as a ſtandard and rule, to reforme and conforme
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152411:9"/>viſible Churches unto, both in their doctrine and practiſe: and that alſo upon occaſion of the corruptions, which by the impoſing of the legal covenant and natural ſeed had invaded them, as is moſt evident to have been the caſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.5.—10. If no ſuch matter at all concerning inviſible faints, any otherwayes conſidered then in viſible Church-order, be to be found in the ſcope and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Apoſtle; which alſo is evident: Then let no perſon give up their reaſon and underſtanding to ſuch impertinent and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coherent interpretations, againſt the plain drift of the Spirit of God, and the work of reformation therein purſued. And thus much of the Covenant of Grace, before the coming of Jeſus Chriſt in the fleſh: wherein we would not be underſtood, in what hath been ſaid touching the abrogation of the legal covenant, to teach the abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of any moral Doctrine or Precept.</p>
            <p>The laſt adminiſtration of the covenant of grace,
<note place="margin">The miniſtry by Chriſt.</note> uſually called the new covenant, is that which was eſtabliſhed by Jeſus Chriſt at his coming, which was altogether of another nature to that which went before it. This was not a covenant miniſtring or ſerving to any doctrine above or beyond it ſelf, as was the other, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.1. But this was the myſtery of the grace of God it ſelf plainly admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred: a myſtery hid from ages and generations, <hi>Goloſ.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.8, 9. It was under a vaile or behind a curtain till Chriſt himſelf came to reveale it; and the whole ſcope of the doctrine prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, runs quite beſide the pretented priveledg of the ſeed after the fleſh, and is placed upon the ſeed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſpirit, as being indeed the true ſeed, who were really ſtated by God in the priviledg of the everlaſting covenant through their new-birth, and not otherwiſe. Mark the preaching and practiſe of <hi>John the Baptiſt, Matth.</hi> 3.8, 9. <hi>Bring forth therefore fruits meet for repentance, and think not to ſay within your ſelves, We have Abraham to our father.</hi> Obſerve the doctrine of Chriſt, upon what foundation he builds the Goſpel-Church, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.18. Upon the profeſſion of actual faith in the Son of God. The birth-priviledg cannot be ſquared by this rule, to have a place in this building. Again, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 54.13. Propheſying of the Goſpel-Church, ſayeth, <hi>And all thy children ſhall be taught of God,</hi> is applyed by Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 6.44, 45. with this intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, <hi>No man can come to me except the father which ſent me draw him,</hi> &amp;c. There is no coming unto Chriſt, nor ſonſhip
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152411:10"/>in the Church upon birth-priviledge any longer. Again, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.26. <hi>If any man come to me, and hate not his father,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be my diſciple;</hi> here is no roome for birth-priviledg to make diſciples to Chriſt, or upon that title to come unto him. Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priviledges are a part of the Goſpel-inheritance, and follow Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonſhip. <hi>If ſous, then heires. Gal.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. Now Goſpel-ſons are not born ſuch, of the will of the fleſh, but of the will of God; <hi>Of his own will begat he us, James</hi> 1.18. And therefore the viſible profeſſion hereof muſt be the common principle to conſtitute viſible children of the Goſpel-covenant, under the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Jeſus Chriſt, by whom grace and truth was admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, not fleſh and figure.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the firſt terme, that came to hand in our opponents firſt propoſition [the Covenant of Grace.] The next expreſſion to be explained, is [ſtands now in force.] It ſeemeth to us an hard kinde of expreſſion, to ſay, That <hi>the Covenant of Grace ſtands now in force:</hi> as if it were capable of being or not being in force, with reſpect to ſeaſons: but thus we underſtand our opponents meaning by this terme, that it ſignifieth a perſon to be compriſed, and ſtated in the covenant of grace by God.</p>
            <p>Another expreſſion craving explanation, is, [the children of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers under the Goſpel] which in our opponents intention, we take not to be ſuch children as were begotten unto the faith by beleevers, and in that reſpect came under that appellation, of which we read, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. 3 <hi>Epiſt. Joh. ver.</hi> 4. But we underſtand it of the children begotten of the bodies of beleevers; and in the ſame ſence and no other, we our ſelves crave to be underſtood throughout this Reply, by the terms of carnal, or natural ſeed, ſeed after the fleſh, ſeed of the birth-priviledge: which caution we premiſe, that theſe terms made uſe of by us be not applyed to ſignify ſome evil quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
            <p>The ſecond propoſition needoth not to have any thing farther ſaid unto, it being dependant upon the firſt, and muſt ſtand and fall with it.</p>
            <p>Theſe things premiſed, we return anſwer to theſe his two propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, <hi>viz.</hi> (1) that the Covenant of grace ſtands now in force to the children of beleevers under the Goſpel. (2) That this is a ſufficient ground by Gods appointment, why children of beleevers ſhould be baptized.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:152411:10"/>
            <p>And firſt, We ſay, If by this term [the Covenant of Grace] in his firſt propoſition, be meant the Covenant of Grace in our firſt acceptation of it; and by [the children of beleevers under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel] be meant their natural ſeed, as before explained: Then we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the firſt Propoſition, becauſe the Covenant of grace in that ſence, is not in force to any, upon any other conſideration, then as they are in Chriſt. Then alſo is the ſecond Propoſition to be denyed; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath made no ſuch appointment, that Baptiſm ſhould be adminiſtred to perſons upon the ſingle ground of election.</p>
            <p>If the Covenant of grace be meant of the covenant of grace mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring, according to our ſecond acceptation: then, if it be alſo meant <hi>to be in force &amp;c.</hi> by vertue of ſome inſtitution, appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God before the coming of Chriſt; we deny the ſecond propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, that that is any ſufficient ground by Gods appointment of Baptizing infants now; ſuch inſtitutions being vaniſhed with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhadows.</p>
            <p>If by the Covenant of Grace, be meant the Covenant of grace as it is now miniſtred ſince the coming of Chriſt; we alſo deny the ſame propoſition in this particular, that there can be found no ſuch appointment inſtituted by Chriſt, or any of his Apoſtles, for the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing of the children of beleevers.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, we ſay, That the Covenant of Grace is always in force to the elect as ſuch, called or uncalled, infants or aged; it is alſo in force to all ſorts of perſons, as it is a doctrine by Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment to be publiſhed, for the calling of ſinners to repentance: but we utterly deny that there is any thing at all in force by the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace, or by any appointment of God, for the baptizing of infants.</p>
            <p>The ordinance of Baptiſm, is a part of the inſtituted worſhip of the Goſpel, and all the force and authority that it hath upon the Conſcience in point of practiſe, is to be derived from the plain and expreſs law and word of God, by which it is made an Ordinance of the goſpel: and that in point of practiſe muſt be the Rule not to be ſwerved from. God hath been very jealous of all his Ordinances, to keep them exactly to his own methods and manner, in the practiſe of them: and the nature of man is very preſumptuous to be interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and medling. Let us not forget that of <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.5. <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.9.—40. See that thou make all things according to the pattern ſhewed to thee in the mount: all inſtituted worſhip, muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152411:11"/>to the heavenly pattern.</p>
            <p>But to follow our opponent in the proof of his propoſitions. <hi>This is evident</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>from many Scriptures in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and ſo gives you an inſtance in that one, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. and then fairly leaves you to make the application as you pleaſe, without managing his authority to prove any one point or term, in either of his propoſitions. But the next work we find him upon, is an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, confuſed accuſation, that the <hi>Anabattiſts</hi> obſcure and dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Scripture, and perſwade the world, that children have no right to the promiſe, till they are actually called. Wherein we ſhall uſe ſome patience, to bear his abuſes, and frothy traverſes, to give an anſwer as God ſhall inable.</p>
            <p>Our ſence of the Scripture alleadged is this: That <hi>ver,</hi> 39. hath a neceſſary and plain coherence, with <hi>verſes</hi> 37, 38. wherein we have an inquiry of the Jew wounded in conſcience for ſin, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles full and comfortable reſolution of the caſe, to this effect; that God hath made his precious promiſe in Chriſt, to Jew and Centile, of pardoning repenting ſinners, and of giving to them the holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and that in this grace and promiſe, the Jew and his children had a precedency, and priority to all other people: and therefore they repenting and being baptiſed, ſhould receive the mercy promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. This reſolution of this Scripture, is not only pertinent to the caſe, but alſo very coherent with it ſelf, and conſonant to other Scriptures. It was a pertinent point for comfort to the Jew, that grace was tendred to all, that all ſcruple from perſonal incapacity, might be removed by ſuch rich mercy: and it was an additional comfort, that the tender of this grace was ſpecially reſerved, to be made to the Jew and his children, before any others; as is elſewhere alſo declared, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.26, 46. But withal it was profitable to inform the Jew (who boaſted much of his birth-pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg) that although he had a priority in the tender, yet as to the grace it ſelf, he was but in a parity and likeneſs with all others; that a right frame of ſpirit, might keep him from being puffed up, under a miſtake of that wherein his Intereſt lay: and this alſo we have elſewhere frequently inſtanced, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.29, 30. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5, 6, 7. And that therefore the ſame common requiſite, of Faith and Repentance, in order to Baptiſm, muſt be found alike in all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that would partake in the benefit of this grace indeed, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15, 16. <hi>He that beleeveth and is baptiſed, &amp;c.</hi> this is the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152411:11"/>Doctrine that Chriſt comanded to be preached to every creature for ſalvation, and this is the order by which it ſhould inure to every creature, firſt that they repent, and then that they be baptiſed. And let not your mindes be ſhifted aſide from this truth, by a pretence that the Spirit of God, in theſe and ſuch-like places of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, is onely to be underſtood of an inviſible work of grace, in the hearts of the ſaints, and not of the principle upon which the Goſpel-Church was to have its conſtitution. (Of which you have formerly in like caſe been warned.) (1.) Jeſus Chriſt came to gather the true ſeed into his granary the Church, and not the chaff;
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.12.</note> and his ſanne, the Goſpel-adminiſtration, was fitted as a fanne to doe the thing according to the doctrine held forth; he came not to ſet up a Church after the Jewiſh principle,
<note place="margin">Mat. 16.18.</note> of a natural generation of the ſons of men, but by ſpiritual regeneration to be made the Sons of God, and therefore tells Peter, that he will build his new Church upon the rock of perſonal profeſſion. And (2.) who ſhall preſume to lay a right in natural generation, as a principle to give an enterance into the viſibility of the Church, of which there is not one titlte to be found in all the New Teſtament, from Chriſt or any A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle? while in the mean time the Scriptures of the Prophets, and all the New Teſtament, doe everywhere abound with evidences that run upon a ſuppoſition of a real profeſſion of a work of grace, as the ſtate of the Goſpel-Church: and many paſſages againſt the principle of a ſeed according to the fleſh, the principle of the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage covenant, as hath been promiſed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas he chargeth us with <hi>perſwading the world to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that children have no right to the promiſe, till they are actually called.</hi> It is a very odious and falſe ſuggeſtion, the man was ill inſtructed to publiſh it; this we ſay, that a right to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, doth not conclude a right to be baptiſed. We affirme that children have a right to the promiſe as well as the aged; but to have a right to be baptiſed, is not given to old or young, till the rule of the word be complied with according to which baptiſme is to be adminiſtred. As for his diſcovery of our miſtake which he thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifieth:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Call]</hi> hath no relation to children, but to them that are afar eſt (1.) Becauſe the children are joyned with their parents in the promiſe, which is an intire propoſition in the Text.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:152411:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſay, that his affirmation, and his reaſon, are of the like worth, both made up of a meer trinkling about words; his reaſon ſuppoſeth, that in a continued diſcourſe, a word in one propoſition can have no relation to words without the ſame; which is ſenſleſs: or that there may not be more then one logical propoſition, in the ſame coherence of matter; which is alſo as vain as the other.</p>
            <p>We have not yet ended with this Scripture, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. We lay our claime to it, as eminently juſtifying our practiſe of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme; and that it ſpeakes not in favour of our oppoſites at all; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though alledged as a chief evidence againſt us, <hi>The promiſe is to you, and to your children, therefore repent, and be baptiſed.</hi> This is part of the Apoſtles argument to the Jew, which plainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers this,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
            </p>
            <p>That the reaſon upon which the title of the Jew, and their child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren to the promiſe was to inure, was repentance, and baptiſme thereupon, otherwiſe there lay no force at all in the Apoſtles argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if the promiſe would inure, where there was not found, in the perſon the preſcribed qualification of repentance,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> antecedent to baptiſme.</p>
            <p>If the children ſhould be admitted to baptiſme before repentance, then the promiſe carries more to the children, then it would afford to the parents, although the parents title to the promiſe, be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed antecedent to the childs, and the childs title, through the parent.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>[call]</hi> in the cloſe of the 39. verſ. is to be reſtrained to them afar off, and to have no relation to children, as is alledged, what a diſproportion would it have produced in the converts to the Church, that the Gentiles, and their children, being compriſed under [them afar off] muſt firſt be called, and then baptiſed; but on the part of the Jewes, the effectuall calling of the parents, and their baptiſm, ſufficed to juſtifie the baptiſme of the children without calling.</p>
            <p>Our Accuſer proceeds with a long train of arguments: we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pick out the coherence they have, with what had been before al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged: we ſhall therefore take them in their courſe, (as the Lord ſhall give aſſiſtance) and make our anſwers to them ſeverally, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking advantage from their inconſequential application, either to his propoſitions or alledged Text.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:152411:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If children ſhould be excluded from the promiſe,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>2</label> this could not have comforted the patents, but have ſadned them, that their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould be the ſame with heathens, but here the ſcope of the Text is urged by the Apoſtle for conſolation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Argument ſuppoſeth our denyal of the promiſe to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> wherein the man runs after his own miſtakes: denyal of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, is no excluſion from the promiſe. As to the odious compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, of children of believers, to heathens (falſly charged on us) we reject. Heathens differ as much from the children of believers in our account, as open Apoſtates doe from hopeful expectants of the Church. As to the point of conſolation, our denyal of the baptiſme of infants, withdraweth from the parent no real ground of conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, founded in the covenant of grace, and applyed by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in this Scripture; but we ſay that the application thereof to particular perſons, if it be not according to Scripture-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ule, will prove a groundleſs fiction, and no conſolation. And as to the infants of believers, we farther ſay, that beſides our aſſurance, that the grace of election, becauſe it is beſtowed without reſpect of perſons, doth reach infants as well as others, and it's likely more frequently the infants of the godly then others. That the infants of believers have alſo a nearneſs not only to the promiſe, but alſo to the fruition of the grace promiſed, by reaſon of many high advantages, which others enjoy not, and among the reſt, that the godly to whom they ſtand related and are committed, have promiſes of being heard of God in their faithful prayers, even to the pardon of ſin, <hi>Job</hi> 1.5. <hi>James</hi> 5.15, 16. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.16. And that therefore there is great ground given to ſuch parents of an holy hope, that God doth hear their prayers for the ſalvation of their infants, ſeeing they are not under that ſin unto death, that is not to be prayed for. And we could never finde our ſobereſt oppoſites, to aſcribe a greater ground for a believer to conclude the ſalvation of his infant if he died after he was baptiſed, then if he did before. Beſides which great advantages, there being alſo reſerved to the children, the ſame tenders of grace, for their full inveſture into the real fruition of the promiſes, we remain yet to be informed what diſcouragement was put upon the parent, labouring under the ſence of guilt, to receive a dectrine thus tendered, bringing with it the ſame grace upon the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152411:13"/>like termes, to be beſtowed upon his poſterity, together with theſe high advantages premiſed.</p>
            <p>We alſo ſay, Whatever benefit may be juſtly ſaid to accrue to the infant by virtue of the promiſe through the baptiſme of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, all that would be more effectually and certainly made out to the comfort of them both, by baptiſme upon faith, then can be by baptiſine in infancie; by how much baptiſme upon faith, more certainly declares the parent by whom the benefit doth accrue, to be really in the covenant, then baptiſme in infancie can be ſaid to doe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. If ſo, then this could not encourage the Parents to ſubmit to Chriſt under this adminiſtration; but would have hindred them, that their children ſhould be excluded from the Promiſe, who ſtood in it two thouſand yeers before, under the other adminiſtration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Argument runs upon the ſame ſuppoſition with the former, (whither we refer the Reader for an Anſwer in part) only there it pretended to ſaddening, here to diſcouragement; here alſo we have the old common miſtake, that an incapacity to Baptiſm excludes from the Promiſe. But to paſs by theſe faul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, we come to what may be further found a colour for an Objection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Infants ſtood viſible members of the Church for two thouſand yeers in the adminiſtration: this adminiſtration excludes them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> They ſtood excluded altogether, as much above two thouſand yeers before Circumciſion, as they do now; ſo that an Ordinance for their Church-memberſhip, was not ſo from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; but came in by ſpecial inſtitution long ſince.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The other adminiſtration in which they ſtood, was eſtabliſhed with a ſeed to be propagated by natural generation, according to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs command, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.9. <hi>Thou ſhalt keep my covenant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, thou and thy ſeed after thee</hi> in their generations <hi>this is my co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which ye ſhall keep,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Every man-child among you ſhall be circumciſed.</hi> But where have we command for the like in this adminiſtration? That adminiſtration was a typical, temporary, bondage-covenant; and in a ſigure it miniſtred unto the ends of the everlaſting covenant; and therefore it ſufficed as unto that admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, if the people, the children of that covenant, were of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152411:13"/>ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> becauſe by that ſhadowy covenant, young and old, good and bad were all alike Covenanters, and all alike in a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to be ſubjects of an adminiſtration, which was to ſerve unto the example and ſhadow of heavenly things, till the ſeed ſhould come to whom the Promiſe was made, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.19. as hath been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly proved, whereunto we reſer the Reader.</p>
            <p>But the Goſpel-adminiſtration, that brings Chriſt, and all the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of his grace, in the truth and reality, and not in the figure and example; is not receptive of children, as to the Principle upon which it ſtands, any other way then upon ſome viſible demonſtration of Faith, whereby Chriſt comes to be received, who are therefore called the ſons of God, <hi>John</hi> 1.12, 13. <hi>As many as received him, to them gave he power,</hi> right or priviledg <hi>to become the ſons of God, to them that believe in his name, borne not of blood</hi> &amp;c. Thus the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4, 28. calls the ſaints of the Churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi> children of the promiſe, in oppoſition to the ſeed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh, verſ. 23. And their mother the free Goſpel-co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, v. 26. And the ſame Apoſtle declareth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9, 8, that the children of the promiſe are counted for the ſeed, in oppoſition to the ſeed according to the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh, v.7. Neither, becauſe they are the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> &amp;c. Whereunto many other ſcriptures might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Yea, the whole ſtream of the New Teſtament, witneſſeth to a ſeed according to calling, and (as to the principle of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion) all living ſtones, for the conſtitution of the Church of God, and not one word in favour of a ſeed according to the fleſh, as to admiſſion into the Church, upon that principle of birth-pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though the Goſpel-Church may not be built by ſuch a ſeed, nor can be receptive of it upon that account; yet would there ariſe no ground of diſcouragement or ſadneſs to the Jew thereby; his ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowy glory was now to ceaſe, but real glory was ſet up in the place of it: and the ſame ſpecially prepared, and held forth to him and his ſeed, as amphe as ever, and by a better and more laſting covenant, to be made good upon better promiſes. But this glory muſt be received as it is tendered; it is tendered to faith, and by faith alone can it be enjoyed and partaken in, and profeſſion the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible title thereunto. And againſt this change, the Jew had nothing to except, but his unbelieving minde which God determined ſhould break him off, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20. The change of the adminiſtration
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152411:14"/>from the carnal ſeed to the ſeed by adoption, did not at all abridge the intereſt of the Jew to the grace of God in Chriſt, or any privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges thereof, but unbeleef.</p>
            <p>We conſent thus far to the truth of the objection,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> that it could not be avaided, but that the Goſpel ſhould become a ſore offence to the carnal Jew, that could not diſcerne the myſtery which was beyond his typical ſtate; which exalted his nation ſo much above other people; and conſequently his children of the fleſh, who were to ſucceed in the like pre-eminence: and all this to ceaſe, and the Gentiles to be admitted into the ſame grace with the ſeed of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham;</hi> was doubtleſs that ſtumbling block which offended many of them, as the Lord had foretold by <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 8.14. applied by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5, — 9. But what of all this? muſt the myſtery of grace, for the gathering of the elect to Chriſt, be ſtill cumbred and clouded with the pretenſions of a carnal ſeed, which could by no meanes be brought to the ſtandard of ſo high a myſtery as Chriſt was come to call men up unto (<hi>viz,</hi> faith, repentance, laying down of life and all for Chriſt in or to the glory promiſed) rather then the Jew muſt take offence? we therefore deny that the argument from ſaddening and offending the carnal Jew, is of any worth at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Arg. 4, If ſo, then children would be ſuperfluous in the Text, and ſo the Spirit of God would be charged with tautologies, which would be blaſphemie to affirme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeemes ſuperfluity and tautologie muſt all be one. But we ſay that our denyal of baptiſme to infants, doth not render the declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the right of the children of the Jew, in this Scripture ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous, becauſe the children of the Jew may have many great rights in the promiſe held forth, and yet through preſent perſonal incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, may not have a right to be baptiſed. Baptiſme is a part of inſtituted worſhip, and muſt be adminiſtred juſt as the law of its inſtitution directeth, and not otherwayes: and it had well become our Accuſer to have found one little place, within ſome of his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, to have convinced us of errour from a rule of the word, whereby this forme of infant-baptiſme came to be a Goſpel-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; or at leaſt ſome example of its practiſe in the manner he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends unto, and to have paſſed by theſe empty notions.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:152411:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Arg. 5. The tenſe is changed: The promiſe is to you and your children, in the preſent tenſe; but when he ſpeakes of the call, he ſpeakes in the future tenſe, as many as God <hi>ſhall</hi> call, which muſt needs be applied to them afar off, and not to children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Muſt it needs be applied to them afar off, and not to children?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Then it muſt needs be, that the Gentiles and their children muſt be all called before baptiſed, for all theſe are meant by them afar off, being oppoſed in the Text to you and your children, that is, the Jew. So that infant-baptiſme can have no place in the Gentile-Church by this interpretation, but muſt remaine with the Jewes by virtue of the promiſe to them and their children before calling.</p>
            <p>This abſurd diſproportion cannot be ſhifted aſide by replying that [them afar off] muſt be limited to the firſt called Gentiles:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> becauſe then there could be no difference at all in the caſe, whether call be applied to the people of the preſent tenſe, the Jew and his children, or to the people of the future tenſe, them afar off; becauſe it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented that the firſt Fathers of the Jewiſh people themſelves muſt be called before baptiſed.</p>
            <p>This trifling diſpute from the change of the tenſe is very abſurd, as well as frothie,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> as ſuppoſing that the ſame qualification of calling may not alſo be requiſite to the preſent time, becauſe it is here ſet down; as required in the future not conſidering that calling muſt reeds be found in the firſt Jewes themſelves. The like abſurdity is in his argument of the change of the tenſe, by his change of the ſubject, from promiſe to call; the promiſe is, the call ſhall be: what is all this to ground an argument upon?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Arg. 6. If their interpretation hold good, there would be a very great change in the extent of the Covenant, narrower under the Goſpel then it was under the Law, and no notice in all the book of God given of ſuch a change.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Paſſing by the unexpreſſed interpretation, we ſhall apply an anſwer to this argument, as it ſtands oppoſed to our practiſe of baptiſme, as the Lord ſhall give ability.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We ſay, That the Covenant hath one and the ſame extent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, under, and ſince the Law, conſidered ſingly in it ſelf:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152411:15"/>is changeable, and was often changed; yet whatever paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from the Believer to his Childe, by vertue of the intrinſecal Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Covenant of Grace, that alſo admits of no change; but being ſo made out, we ſay, That all that will be more evidently and cleerly ratified, both to Parent and Childe, for the comfort of both, by Baptiſm after Faith, then by Baptiſm in Infancy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Neither is the adminiſtration under the Goſpel, narrower then that under the Law, becauſe it admits not Infant-baptiſin. This adminiſtration under the Law, was circumſcribed to a little Land, and a ſmall People: the bounds of the other are ſtretched from Sea to Sea; and from the Flood to the Worlds end. This was reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſeed and family of <hi>Abraham;</hi> the other extended to the ſeed and family of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> This had its exiſtence but two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeers, upon an occaſional temporary principle, the other is ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to anſwer a principle exiſting from everlaſting to everlaſting. This adminiſtration was the ſhadow, figure, and example; the other the ſubſtance. This was the Handmaid; the other the Miſtris. And if the caſe be thus between theſe two adminiſtrations, will any preſume to charge the Goſpel-adminſtration with more narrowneſs, then the Law; becauſe of the diſ-continuance of the Birth-Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Although the Grace of the Goſpel be extended far beyond the Grace under the Law; yet as to Perſons, the Children of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel are formed to ſo ſtrict and refined a qualification, that in that reſpect we allow the Law, a latitude beyond the Goſpel; but yet with this mark. That that indulgence of the Law was one of the great imperfections, which the Goſpel came to reform, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.10, 11, 12. And of this change the Book of God doth give abundant no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, although the Accuſer be informed to the contrary, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.10. <hi>Caſt out the bond-woman, and her ſon,</hi> &amp;c. Shortly after the inſtitution of the Ordinance of Circumciſion, for the Priviledge of the Seed according to the fleſh, the Lord brings forth a Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical inſtance in the very Family of <hi>Abraham,</hi> (the type of the true Church) wherein this great change of Church-Priviledge was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to be taken from the carnal Seed, that it ſhould be given to the Seed according to Grace, under the Goſpel-adminiſtration. And to put that matter out of queſtion, we have the unvailing of this Prophetical inſtance to the very ſame purpoſe, in <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.30. ſo alſo, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.1. <hi>Sing O barren thou that beareſt not.</hi> What ſhe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152411:15"/>was, the Apoſtle tells you, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.26, 27. next conſider her husband, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Thy Maker is thy Husband, the Lord of hoſts is his Name; and thy Redeemer the holy One of Iſrael:</hi> at <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. you have the refined qualification of her Children and People, <hi>And all thy children ſhall be taught of the Lord.</hi> Here you have a Prophetical deſcription of the Goſpel-Church-ſtate, which the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of a fleſhly extraction from the moſt ſanctified Saints, cannot poſſibly compare unto, it muſt therefore neceſſarily be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of another Seed, even of a Seed begotten of God by the Word of Truth, <hi>James</hi> 1.18. the Goſpel-People. And this was a fair notice given of the change in queſtion, to wit, narrower, as to the qualification of the Perſons, but more extended in Grace. To the like effect is <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.1. <hi>Ariſe, and ſhine,</hi> &amp;c. at <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. <hi>Thy people alſo ſhall be all righteous.</hi> Another fair warning for the fleſhly Seed, is <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.15. <hi>For the Lord God ſhall ſlay thee, and call his people by another name.</hi> What think you of this warning? Hear the Prophet <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.31. <hi>The days come that I will make a new covenant</hi> &amp;c. <hi>verſ.</hi> 34. <hi>They ſhall all know me from the leaſt of them to the greateſt of them.</hi> Here is a plain notice of the change of the old adminiſtration, which gloried in the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> after the fleſh, and as plainly foretelling the ceſſation of that propagation, to give place to the new adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the true Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Seed according to the Spirit; and indeed the change of the adminiſtration neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves the fleſhly Seed, becauſe it hath a ſtanding by no other right then what it had under that Covenant. We ſhall not make uſe of the New Teſtament to proſecute this point, it everywhere abounds with evidence to it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And becauſe the Accuſer placeth the force of an Argument upon the ſuppoſition of not giving notice of the change of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of viſible admiſſion into the Church; we alſo ſhall take the ſame liberty of reaſoning, and ſay, That ſeeing the common way of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to baptiſm in the Primitive Church, was after perſonal Profeſſion of Faith; and alſo ſeeing the error of circumciſing ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptized Diſciples, had generally overſpread the Churches, and might be interpreted very much in favour of the fleſhly ſeed, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. it is very ſtrange, that notwithſtanding the common practice of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm upon Profeſſion, and notwithſtanding the ſevere Confutation of this, and the like error, by Arguments plainly in diſ-favour of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152411:16"/>the carnal Seed, as may appear <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.10, 11, 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13, 14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.7, 8. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.30. yet that in neither caſe, there ſhould be found anywhere in all the New Teſtament, a qualification for the ſaving of the right of Infants of Believers to Baptiſm, if it had been a right, eſpecially upon that pertinent occaſion about circumciſion: we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conclude, that there was not ſuch right.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Arg. 7. <hi>If their interpretation be true, then the believing Jews, ſhould have loſs by their repentance, if their children ſhould be excluded from the Promiſe, as ſoon as the Parents had repented.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Very true, and a greater loſs then that would befal the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, if the Parents repentance ſhould exclude them from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. But where did the Accuſer learn that Interpretation and Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? we utterly diſown it, and do place it among the other calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies unjuſtly thruſt upon the Profeſſion of the Truth wherein we ſtand. We ſay, That the Children have a right in the Promiſe with the Parent; and that the Parents Repentance and Baptiſm, brings great advantages to the Childe: but we deny that a right to the Promiſe infers a right to be baptized. The Scripture alledged, declares a right unto the Promiſe in theſe Jews, when they had no right to be baptized; the right to be baptized, ariſeth from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Rule preſcribed by God's word for the adminiſtration of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm, and the Perſons conformity thereunto. Among all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes in this Queſtion, when ſhall we be preſſed with a rule pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing Infant-Baptiſm, as a part of the inſtituted worſhip of the Goſpel-adminiſtration?</p>
            <p n="2">2. We conſear, that in ſome ſenſe, a Jew converted to the Goſpel ſhould have loſs, and particularly in that point of ſealing his fleſhly Seed by an Ordinance, together with the fall of all the glory of their Sanctuary, and pompous Prieſthood, ſo much and ſo long the joy and boaſting of that Nation: which the Spirit of God fore-ſaw and foretold, by <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.14. and hence it come to paſs, that Chriſt became ſo great an Offence, and the Goſpel ſo ſore a Stone of ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling and Rock of offence to them all; yea, even to many of them after they had ſubmitted to the Goſpel: yea, the Gentile Churches were ſcarce, if at all, preſerved from ſtumbling hereat with the Jew. But all this loſs well conſidered, would amount to no more then what
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152411:16"/>befalls a man, who from the Priviledges of a Servant, is inveſted into the Priviledges of a Son. And this was the very caſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. <hi>God ſent forth his Son,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>To redeem them that were under the law, that we might receive the adoption of Sons.</hi> Verſ. 7. <hi>Wherefore thou art no more a ſervant, but a ſon.</hi> And the reaſon of this change, the Apoſtle plainly ſheweth us, <hi>verſ.</hi> 23. <hi>He that was after the bond-woman, was born after the fleſh; but he of the free-woman, was by promiſe.</hi> There was an infinite dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in the propagation of the Seed of the former Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and of the Seed of the Goſpel-ſtate; no leſs then between Nature, and the Power of God, as was in the Types, <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Neither hath this change brought any other loſs unto the child, but, 1. The Intereſt which it had in the everlaſting Covenant, under the former adminiſtration, it ſtill retains. 2. The benefits and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages which it had by the Parent, are ſo much bettered, by how much the ſpiritual ſtate of the Parent under the Goſpel, by Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm after Faith, is better ratified then under the Law. 3. All o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and further benefits from the Covenant, are more freely and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tendered, and with many enforcing advantages, brought neer to be had and enjoyed. 4. It is an advantage, that as a token of the expiration of the bondage Church-ſtate, their ſigning upon the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural birth, is alſo at an end; and their ſealing into all theſe Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, transferred to an Ordinance upon the viſible Title of their New-birth; without which, no word of God can be found to raiſe them into the viſible Dignity and Prerogative of the Sons and Heirs of <hi>Sarah,</hi> the Goſpel-Covenant or adminiſtration. And it is cleer to us, that ſuch a loſs as this, was not obſcurely pointed at, in the preaching of Chriſt, although we do not ſtrain it here, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.26. a loſs of natural and carnal Ordinances, to enjoy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There is no colour of warrant from the Word of God, That Jeſus Chriſt, in the day of his appearing, did eſtabliſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one Ordinance in the Church, which did import a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in his Interceſſion, to be practicable duely by a perſon in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate ſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Arg. <hi>Then they could have no hope of their children; for hope without a promiſe, is preſumption.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:152411:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Auſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. If the hope of the Parent for his child's ſalvation be grounded upon the adminiſtration of an Ordinance in Infancy, then neither had the Patriarks for above two thouſand yeers hope of their children: which we finde falſe by <hi>Noah's</hi> Propheſie, <hi>Gen.</hi> 29.26, 27.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We demand what hopes the Accuſer intendeth? and by what Scriptures the ſame are annexed to the adminiſtration of an Ordinance in Infancy?</p>
            <p n="3">3. VVe juſtifie an holy hope in Believers, in behalf of their Children; which is grounded upon plain Scriptures, without Infant-Baptiſm.</p>
            <p n="4">4. VVe ſay. That this Argument ſeemeth to carry in it this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion. That Chriſtian People, by Infants Baptiſm, are by Scripture-grounds aſſured, according to Goſpel-hope, of the Salvation of their Children: there wants a proof for it; and we ſuppoſe, it is not received as a Truth by many that oppoſe us in this Point.</p>
            <p n="5">5. His Argument ſuppoſeth, That to be without Infants Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm, will infer a being without the Promiſe; but that hath been often diſclaimed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Arg. 9. <hi>If children ſhould be excluded from the Promiſe, let any man breathing ſhew me what priviledge the Children of repenting Parents have above others? Now it is cleer the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle adds children in the Text, to ſhew that they had ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial priviledge above thoſe that were uncalled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſuppoſition of this Argument is, That the denial of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm to the Infants of repenting Parents, deprives them of all Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges above the Infants of Perſons uncalled: but this ſuggeſtion hath been formerly replied unto, in our Anſwer to the Accuſer's ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Argument; where alſo, many high Priviledges of the Infants of the Godly, are expreſly mentioned.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Accuſer doth not ſhew us how the Apoſtles words, <hi>[the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is to you and to your children]</hi> being made uſe of to win an unwilling People to the Faith, do prove the Baptiſm of the Infants of thoſe that are actually in the Faith, ſeeing it will not be granted, that a right to the Promiſe, and a right to be baptized, are converti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble terms.</p>
            <p n="3">3. VVe have already ſet down many Priviledges of the Infants of believers, above others; although we admit them not to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152411:17"/>or viſible-Church memberſhip. If we detract from them any ſpiritual participation in the grace of the covenant, we believe we had not been ſo long left under a general charge, without ſome particular allegation againſt us. But we are well aſſured, that no ſuch thing in particular can be juſtly found againſt us. Beſides we know that our oppoſites among themſelves are ſo puzled about the finding out more priviledges to the infants of believers, then we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low (ſave in the ſingle point of admiſſion to baptiſme) that although there have been ſufficient demands of it, we doe not know that the ſame hath hitherto been done: and yet ſtill the cry is up in general words, for the priviledges of the infants of believers, as if we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed their poſſibility of ſalvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 10. Then how could the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> come to the Gentiles, according to <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14. which bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> was, I will be a God to thee and to thy ſeed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſuppoſition of this argument being not expreſt we take to be this: If the infants of believing Gentiles be not to be baptiſed, then could not the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham,</hi> mentioned <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14. come to the Gentiles; I am a God to thee and to thy ſeed, &amp;c. To this argument we reply:</p>
            <p>Two places we have in this <hi>third</hi> to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> in which the bleſſing of God to <hi>Ahraham</hi> is intimated. (1.) In the cloſe of verſ. 8. <hi>In thee ſhall all Nations be bleſſed.</hi> (2.) And at v. 16. <hi>To Abraham and to his ſeed were the promiſes made.</hi> As to the firſt place, verſ. 8. it is taken out of <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.3. And becauſe there is a neceſſary coherence of this authority with verſ. 7. for the proof of what is here affirmed <hi>viz. That they which are of faith, the ſame are the children of Abraham;</hi> and becauſe the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is alſo affirmed by this Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. <hi>That he might be the father of all them that believe,</hi> and at verſ. 16. to the ſame effect. <hi>Who is the father of us all:</hi> And is alſo confit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at verſ. 17. by a place alledged out of <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.5. <hi>I have made thee a father of many nations;</hi> We therefore ſay, That theſe two places, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.3. and <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.5. have an agreement between themſelves, becauſe they both agree in the proof of the ſame poſition; <hi>viz.</hi> that they which are of the faith, are the children of <hi>Abraham.</hi> But although this bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> to come on
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152411:18"/>the Gentiles through Jeſus Chriſt (as is expreſſed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14. by a continued and neceſſary coherence of the matter there treated of, falleth in with that which went before, quite againſt the title of the birth-priviledg, eſtabliſhed by the law, and giveth it to believers the only ſons of <hi>Abraham</hi> in the Goſpel-day, verſ. 7. <hi>They which are of faith, the ſame are the children of Abraham.</hi> This bold oppoſite hath pleaſed to lay aſide that bleſſing, and to call upon another Scripture managed by the Apoſtle in another argument, and to annex it with this verſ. 14. to ſerve his turne, but with as little advantage as if he had ſtayed where he was. In the interim, we deny that there is any colour of truth in this allegation, that the denyal of infants-baptiſme bars the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> from the Gentiles, or can be juſtly ſuppoſed ſo to doe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But admitting his application, of verſ. 16. drawn from <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. <hi>I will be a God to thee, and thy ſeed after thee,</hi> to be pertinent: Yet it makes not a jot to his purpoſe, to wit, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the carnal-ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> had a day, wherein as the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſons of <hi>Abraham</hi> they were priviledged under circumciſion; that therefore the carnal-ſeed of every believer ſhould in the Goſpel-day, be admitted into the viſible priviledges of ſons and heirs of Chriſt. It is a very froward ſuppoſition, that the proportion between <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> in the fleſh and his carnall ſeed, in the time when circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was in date, ſhould be the ſame to <hi>Abraham</hi> in the ſpirit, (who is Chriſt) and the carnal ſeed of every believer in that ſeaſon when circumciſion is out of date.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What is this ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> to whom God doeth here promiſe to be a God? or what hath blinded the man, that hath conſidered the 16 verſ. and cannot ſee what interpretation the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit makes of his own words in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. <hi>He ſayeth not, Unto ſeeds, as of many; but as of one, And to thy ſeed, which is Chriſt?</hi> Not the natural children of all believers, unleſs men will turne Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, and ſay that Chriſt is given with every natural procreation. For Chriſt, even that ONE is that ſeed, to whom or in whom the promiſe is made, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But this muſt be Chriſt myſtical, and that will ſerve to take in the natural ſeed of believers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> No, it is not Chriſt myſtical: at verſ. 17. the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is confirmed of God in this Chriſt, the Chriſt who is given for a covenant of the people. Although by adoption believers are joynt-heires
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152411:18"/>with Chriſt, yet are they not (and much leſs are their natural ſeed) joynt-mediators with him in the covenant. That Chriſt was the ſole Mediator in the everlaſting covenant, <hi>confirmed</hi> to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> by the covenant of circumciſion; that the promiſe by faith of Jeſus Chriſt might be given to them that believe, is the plain uſe and improvement of this Scripture in this place. But what if Chriſt my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical be alſo taken in to helpe the matter? when will it be proved that God hath made the birth-priviledg a way under the Goſpel-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, to be ingrafted into Chriſt myſtical?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Take this diſtinction concerning the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> in the letter and according to the Law.</item>
               <item>2. The bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> in the myſtery and according to the Goſpel.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. According to the letter, <hi>Abraham</hi> obtained the bleſſings and priviledges of the whole inheritance, which came by the Law to be the peculiar inheritance of himſelf, his fleſhly-ſeed and family, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with all the ſingular advantages which thereby were mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred among them for the calling and gathering of a ſeed to Chriſt, in an everlaſting covenant, whereunto that covenant in which they ſtood under circumciſion, with the prerogatives of the inheritance thereof, did miniſter, as an example, figure and ſhadow. The ſum of the covenant of circumciſion, ſee <hi>Gen,</hi> 17.10. <hi>This is my co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which ye ſhall keep between me and you, and thy ſeed after thee: every man-childe among you ſhall be circumciſed,</hi> unto verſ. 15. That circumciſion was of the ſame nature with the Law, ſee <hi>Lev.</hi> 12.2, 3. <hi>John</hi> 7.23, That the Law was a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant miniſtring as an example, figure and ſhadow of heavenly things, to wit, of the ſanctuary and of the true Tabernacle whereof Chriſt alone was the high-prieſt and miniſter, See <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.1, 2, 5. Chap. 9. verſ. 1. and 9. Chap. 10 verſ. 1. That the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of circumciſion fell with the Law, ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 15.24. <hi>Subver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting your ſoules, ſaying, ye muſt be circumciſed, and keep the Law, Col.</hi> 2.14. In this ſence, the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> was not to come to the Gentiles, neither conſequently the birth-priviledg, which had its inſtitution from that covenant only, and was a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal part of the bleſſing thereby given.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> in the myſtery and according to the Goſpel, is the manifeſtation of Jeſus Chriſt, with all the bleſſings and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152411:19"/>priviledges of the everlaſting covenant to be the peculiar priviledge, inheritance &amp; right of every believer, who therefore are called the children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that the type and the ſubſtance having a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and reſpective application each to other, the minde of God might be clearly ſeen in them both, for the diſtinguiſhing of ſhadows and figures, which were to be done away, from the ſubſtance that was not capable of any change: which we are manifeſtly inſtructed in by the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26. <hi>Ye are all the children of God by faith in Chriſt,</hi> Jew, Greek, bond, free, male, female: mark how the Apoſtle reſolves the point in queſtion, at verſ. 29. <hi>And if ye be Chriſts, then are ye Abrahams ſeed, and heires according to the promiſe.</hi> Not, if ye be the ſeed of believers, then are ye <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, as the Accuſer would inſinuate to the Reader by his half-faced argument. And this is the bleſsing of <hi>Abraham,</hi> which was to come to the Gentiles, even this, that Chriſt with all his benefits ſhould be given to the believing Gentiles for a covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 11. Then how can believers be heires according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. if their children ſhould be excluded from the promiſe? for the childrens right to the promiſe is a part of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers inheritance (for) the promiſe is to thee and thy ſeed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We ſhall not be perſwaded to entertain that poſition, that the children of believers are excluded from the promiſe. We ſay, that as the denyal of infant-baptiſmes imports no excluſion from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, ſo neither doth every right to the promiſe inſtate a perſon into the inheritance.</p>
            <p>The Jew had a right to the promiſe uncalled. (1.) As God had his remnant among them according to election. (2.) He had a right to the promiſe, as God gave him a priority and precedencie in the tenders of the promiſe, above and before all other people. (3.) They had a right to the promiſe, as they were loſt ſinners whom Chriſt came to ſeeke and ſave. But in neither of theſe reſpects was the Jew an heire in the promiſe: ſuch an intereſt and right to the promiſe, declares the perſon to be made a ſon by adoption; and if ſons, then heires of God through Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.7. a priviledge which no title of the natural father can prefer a creature unto in the Goſpel-adminiſtration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Scripture made uſe of for infant-baptiſme in this argument
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152411:19"/>is this, <hi>If ye be Chriſt's, then are ye Abram's ſeed, and heirs, according to the promiſe:</hi> and the application of this Authority, is made by way of queſtion: <hi>If Infants of believers may not be baptized, then how can believers be heirs?</hi> And hath the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon this Scripture in his eye, and yet pretends himſelf unprovided of an anſwer? How plainly doth this Scripture lay the Title of the Heir upon this conditional qualification, of being Chriſts? He that is Chriſts, is an heir by this Text, be his Children never ſo great ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eas and ſtangers.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But ſaith he, <hi>The childrens right to the promiſe, is part of the fathers inheritance: for the promiſe is to thee, and to thy ſeed.</hi> His meaning ſeemeth to be this: If the Father be Chriſt's, and ſo cometh to be an Heir, then the promiſe carrieth the ſame Title to the Inheritance, down to the children: which is all one, as if he had ſaid, That if the Father be a Son of <hi>Abraham,</hi> (which in Goſpel-conſtruction is a believer) then the childe muſt be a Son of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and a believer alſo; even by his Birth-Priviledge, and not by Faith: directly confronting many Scriptures, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the bleſſing of Sonſhip to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the Inheritance in all manner of perſons to Faith in Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.9. <hi>They which are of faith, are bleſſed with faithful Abraham:</hi> not, they which are the Children of Believers. And in the Text al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, <hi>If ye be Chriſts, then are ye Abrahams:</hi> not, if ye be children of believers.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As to the interpretation of that paſſage, taken from <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. <hi>The promiſe is to Abraham, and to his ſeed;</hi> beſides what hath been ſaid in anſwer to the tenth Argument, we ſay, that the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of this Scripture muſt be made between competent perſons, and under their proper qualifications and reſpects, reſpectively con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. The promiſe was made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> as a common An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtor; and he had a noble ſeed, to whom the bleſſing, as an Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance did inure; but under this qualification, as they were his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ſeed, priviledged under the typical adminiſtration: by which this Prerogative was ſo ſetled. Now to improve this Scripture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, the heavenly myſtery vailed in this diſpenſation, muſt be ſought out: and firſt we muſt finde the common Anceſtor, and him the Apoſtle diſcovers to us to be Chriſt; <hi>if Chriſt's, then Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham's ſeed,</hi> verſ. 29. So then, although <hi>Abraham</hi> ſtood a Father of many Nations, under the Law, yet Chriſt is the onely Father, the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152411:20"/>everlaſting Father under the Goſpel-adminiſtration: and this Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor hath alſo his Seed more nobly deſcended, then the Seed of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham: they are all the Sons of God by faith in Chriſt,</hi> verſ. 26. Yea, it is impoſſible, that by any other qualification, men can come to be the Sons of this Anceſtor; then by being made one with him in the participation of the everlaſting Grace of the unchangeable Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. Now then, it is an incompetent application of perſons, to compare every particular believer and his children to <hi>Abraham,</hi> the common Anceſtor of a whole adminiſtration, and the Seed privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged thereby: and no leſs incompetent, is the application of the qualification requiſite in perſons to be accounted heirs, that becauſe it ſufficed to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s heirs, that they were the ſons of his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Generation, and thereby made capable of an Inheritance in the figure, and in the letter; that therefore it ſufficeth, by being the child according to natural generation of any believer, to be upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count an heir of God, and joynt-heir with Chriſt, in the very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and myſtery, which the former adminiſtration did prefigure. We therefore ſhall deny the Argument raked up out of theſe two abuſed Scriptures: and we ſay, That it is an abſurd, as well as a preſumptuous reaſoning from the promiſe to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his ſeed, to infer or ſuppoſe, that the Infants of believers are joynt-heirs with Chriſt and their godly Parents, under the adminiſtration of Grace, becauſe of the Birth-Priviledge given to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his Seed by the Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 12. <hi>Laſtly, If children be excluded from the promiſe, it ſeems the Apoſtle went about rather to deceive his hearers, then to inform them: it's very unlikely, the Apoſtle would uſe the ſame dialect of the Covenant, that was formerly uſed to</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, <hi>(I am thy God, and the God of thy ſeed: the promiſe is to you and your children) if it had been his minde that children ſhould be excluded. I wiſh that men would with unbyaſſed hearts weigh theſe things, and you ſhall ſee, that the children of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers are in the promiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We ſay, That the Apoſtle in plain terms tells them, That <hi>the promiſe is to you, and to your children:</hi> and in the ſtrength of that gracious promiſe, perſwades them to Repentance and Baptiſm: but
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152411:20"/>what if Children be not excluded from the promiſe? where comes in Infant-Baptiſm upon that account? and this ſhould have been the very firſt thing, if he had intended ingenuouſly to have proceeded; and there was a fair occaſion for it in the firſt Propoſition, That the Covenant of Grace ſtands now in force to the children of Believers under the Goſpel. But in ſtead of a fair proof, as well there, as all along, we have a parcel of doubtful and equivocal terms, made uſe of, without any diſcovery in what ſenſe they are applied: of which artifice, we have frequent experience. And we have ſome grounds to judge, by the management of what hath paſſed, That the Opponent durſt not open that door, leſt the light thereby entring, would have manifeſted theſe, and the like inconſequential and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed reaſonings: and that therefore it was thought beſt, ſilently to truſt the credit of that Point, with the good diſpoſition of the credulous Reader, having to deal with us, whom in a jeer he ſcorns, with the Title of <hi>a learned company,</hi> meaning <hi>a company of ſilly follows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. What an odious and audacious inference, he here impoſeth upon the Spirit of God, That <hi>if Infant-baptiſm may not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from the words alledged, The promiſe is to you, and to your children; then the Apoſtles uſe of them is in a deceit:</hi> we have already made known, That the uſe made of theſe words, was to induce poor grieved ſinners to Repentance, as containing a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine full of comfort for ſuch, that repenting, and being baptized, they and theirs, in all generations, had Promiſes of Chriſt, and all his benefits. And what is the deceit herein? Indeed, to promiſe an Inheritance in Chriſt to poor Creatures; and to affix a Seal of God to that Promiſe, without any colour of authority by any Rule of the Word, may perhaps be in time charged as a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious deceit: the good Lord draw all his faithful Servants out of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Apoſtle uſeth the like (Dialect, as he pleaſeth to ſet it out) phraſe of ſpeech to theſe Infants, that God was pleaſed to uſe to <hi>Abraham</hi> at the confirmation of the Covenant, <hi>[viz. I am thy God and the God of thy ſeed; the promiſe is to you and to your children]</hi> is no help to Infant-baptiſm at all: foraſmuch as the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legation of the Apoſtle, is to perſwade the People to Repentance and Baptiſm; without which, the Promiſe contributed nothing at all to juſtifie a perſons Baptiſm.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:152411:21"/>4. Theſe words ſpoken by God to <hi>Abraham,</hi> [<hi>I am thy God,</hi> &amp;c.] did Prophetically and mainly refer to Chriſt, and Goſpel-times, to have their accompliſhment for the gathering in of the Seed of God to Chriſt, ſcattered abroad amongſt the Jews and Gentiles; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, and firſt of the Jews; it was therefore neceſſary, that the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the Apoſtle ſhould be formed to the likeneſs of the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from whence it is drawn; but ſtill the intepretation ſuited to the minde of the Spirit, to wit, the gathering of a ſpiritual, not a carnal Seed to <hi>Abraham,</hi> that is, Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Further, I obſerve, that the promiſe is to be conſidered two ways:</hi> 1. <hi>As it is inviſibly made, ſo it is alone to the elect.</hi> 2. <hi>As it is viſibly made, ſo it is with viſible profeſſors and their children: whoever is in covenant in the firſt ſenſe, can never fall away; but many may be in covenant in the later ſenſe, who may afterwards degenerate and fall away. Here let the impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Reader take notice, that the Covenant, as it is viſibly exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited is the ground for baptiſm, ſeeing the ſubjects of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant internally are known to God alone. This diſtinction of the Covenant is clear, from</hi> Rom. 9.4. <hi>where the Apoſtle ſaith, The Covenant pertains to them: and yet the Apoſtle was in great heavineſs for them,</hi> verſ. 2. <hi>It's clear from</hi> Act. 3.25. <hi>where the Jews are called the children of the Covenant, and yet but few of them internally in the Covenant. It's clear, from</hi> John 1.11. <hi>where they are called God's own: which could not be by Creation; for ſo, all are his own: neither could it be by ſpecial Grace; For, ſaith the Text they rejected Chriſt: then it muſt needs follow, that there was a viſible Church-Covenant, or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, viſibly exhibited, that gave them a claim to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He calls upon the impartial Reader to take notice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo alſo do we; and ſhall take it for the point in iſſue between us and our Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent, <hi>viz.</hi> whether the viſible exhibition of the Covenant, the ground of Baptiſm, will juſtifie the baptizing of Infants, or the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm of Believers: and let the Reader conſider the evidence, and paſs a righteous ſentence. The viſible exhibition of the Covenant, is not that which the fancy and pleaſure of men calleth ſo; but it is the viſible way of worſhip, which ſtandeth and muſt ſtand by ſpecial
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152411:21"/>inſtitution and appointment of God himſelf, under known or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and laws reveaſed in the word of God: a deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof we have <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.11, 12. <hi>Shew them the form of the houſe, and the faſhion thereof, and the goings out thereof, and the comings in thereof, and all the forms thereof, and all the Ordinances thereof, and all the forms thereof, and all the Laws thereof, and write them in their ſight, that they may keep the whole form thereof, and all the Ordinancas thereof, and doe them: this is the Law of the houſe, upon the top of the mountain, the whole limit thereof round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſhall be moſt holy; behold, this is the Law of the houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we have a compleat deſcription of a viſible exhibition of the covenant, where we may ſee the Lords exactneſs to give his people an unqueſtionable plain written rule, for all viſible worſhip, with this caution, that <hi>the whole limit thereof round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſhall be moſt holy:</hi> nothing to be taken from it, or added to it. So did heat firſt by Moſes, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.9,—40. Now we ſay, if ſuch exactneſs were to be kept in the figure; and a ſutable faithfulneſs was found in the ſervant, what exactneſs may we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from Chriſt the Lord! ſee <hi>Hob.</hi> 3.5, 6. Moſes verily was faithful in all his houſe as a ſervant, for a <hi>TESTIMONY</hi> of thoſe things that were to be ſpoken after; but Chriſt as a Son over his own houſe, which houſe we are. And that Chriſt was not wanting to us in this matter, ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. but the adminiſtration of baptiſm is a very main ordinance of the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted worſhip of the New Teſtament; and that form of it which is practiſed among us, to wit, to baptiſe upon faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, being an undoubted form inſtituted, and practiſed, by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and no inſtitution or practiſe for bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing infants being produced: We therefore ſay, that allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this diſtinction of the promiſe or covenant, inviſibly and viſibly made, and that the viſible exhibition is the ground of baptiſm; we require the proof of this, that infant-baptiſm is a part of the viſible exhibition of the Covenant in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament days, inſtitured by Chriſt or his Apoſtles; and it is no ſmall comfort to us, that in a day of ſo much contradiction, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and detraction, wherein this truth becoms a word of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to us all, hitherto we have never been preſſed by any one argument, which doth pretend to an inſtitution of Chriſt, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Apoſtle, but by certain far-fetcht reaſons from <hi>Abrahams</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:152411:22"/>carnal ſeed, and from circumciſion, and ſuppoſitions of ſtrange inconveniences imagined by men, to follow the denyal of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-baptiſm, and ſuch like matters; and indeed being tryed, are found ſuppoſitions, and nothing elſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a word, this muſt be acknowledged by the</hi> Anabaptiſts <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, elſe how can they call themſelves a viſible Church of Chriſt, if there be no viſible exhibition of the Covenant, to give men ſuch a viſible relation? for there is no claym to God but by Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have heard us affirm a viſible exhibition of the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing covenant; and that in Goſpel-times, the ſame is of another nature then it was under the Law: that now it conſiſteth in a clear unvailed diſcovery of the doctrine of ſalvation by Chriſt, and an orderly diſpoſition of all matters relating to the ſame, by the rule of the written word of God, inſtituting the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament-adminiſtration: all which we thus particularly ſet down once more.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The exhibition is the only inſtituted worſhip which God accepteth; and in performing the ſame according to rule, we are ſaid to do that which is right in the eyes of God, and not otherwiſe: <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.13. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.28.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All the force and authority which it hath upon the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, lyeth in the rule by which it is commanded, and binds ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to it, and no farther. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 8.20. <hi>To the Law and to the Teſtimony, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. God ſo greatly deteſteth all ſervices which himſelf hath not commanded, that in this reſpect he declareth, that <hi>he is a jealous God,</hi> who will not indure a provocation: <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.4, 5. and becauſe mans nature is prone to be inventing and medling, God hath therefore never left his Church without certain plain and poſitive rules for all manner of duties, which he requireth. And this proviſion being as needful in the Goſpel as under the Law, Chriſt therefore was not wanting to the Church therein, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. And amongſt other the Lords Ordinances, we find a plain rule and inſtitution, for the baptiſing of beleevers and penitents; but for the baptiſing of infants, we have not a word: and becauſe we do not read it neither in precept nor preſident, we dare not to practiſe the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:152411:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In this ſence we are to underſtand the children of beleevers in the promiſe, according to the meaning of the Apoſtle, in</hi> Acts 2.39.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is to ſay, theſe words of the Apoſtle, <hi>The promiſe is to you, and to your children,</hi> by him preached to the Jew, to bring them to Chriſt by repentance and baptiſm, do import, that the children of beleevers are in the covenant viſibly exhibited ſuch wretched abuſes of Scripture this bold perſon dares to affirm. That the intereſt of the Jew and his children before repentance and baptiſm is here expreſſed to be in the promiſe of Chriſt, is plain: but from theſe words to conclude an intereſt; yea, an actual being in the viſible Church, would alſo conclude, that the Jew in his rankeſt oppoſition, was already in that ſtate, which the Apoſtle laboured by the tenders of this grace to bring him into.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now this covenant-right, is a ground, which God himſelf lays down, why any ſhould be baptiſed,</hi> Acts 2.38. <hi>he requires bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, v.</hi> 39. <hi>ſhews the reaſon,</hi> for the promiſe is to you. <hi>Here I deſire the reader to take notice, how the word of command, depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the word of promiſe, and what an inſeparable union and connexion there is between the command and the promiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a moſt falſe and ſenſleſs inference: the right to the promiſe we grant to be the ground of the Apoſtles perſwaſion to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and baptiſm; but it is no ground of a perſons being bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized without repentance, neither is it ſo layd down by the Lord, or by the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>But obſerve the dealing of this man, <hi>he requires baptiſm</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>v.</hi> 38. and what next? <hi>ſhews the reaſon,</hi> v. 39. <hi>the promiſe is to you, and to your children:</hi> and then on he runs, that <hi>the word of command depends upon the word of promiſe with an inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble union and connexion,</hi> without taking notice of the conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal qualification of repentance, no leſs in the command (as he hath deviſed to call it) then baptiſm, yea antecedent to it. What wonder, if a corrupt mind drive a perſon headlong to maintain a juſtification of ſmaller, by greater evils? Having firſt found out in the Apoſtles declaration of a right to the promiſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152411:23"/>in perſons, in order to converſion; that the ſame imports a right in a viſible Church-ſtate; That here again, he alſo hath found out a command for baptiſm (disjoyned from a comand to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent) with an inſeparable union and connexion, directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the letter of the text?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſame reaſon alleadged by the Apoſtle, why the parent ſhould be baptiſed, is rendred by the ſame Apoſtle, as a reaſon why the children ſhould be baptiſed,</hi> (for the promiſe is to you and to your children.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the accuſer, whoever he be, enjoy what he demands: we conſent to him herein, that the reaſon of the baptiſm of the parent, is the reaſon of the baptiſm of the child: but the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the baptiſm of the parent, by vertue of this right in the promiſe, cannot take effect at all, or for ever, without the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification of repentance: and if the reaſon rendred by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, be the ſame for the baptiſing of the child, then it muſt bring repentance with it to the water, as the <hi>Eunuch</hi> did faith to <hi>Philip,</hi> or it can receive no baptiſm, if the Apoſtles reaſon be rightly alleadged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nay, the very ſame command expreſſed to baptiſe the one, is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to baptiſe the other: for if ſome, or any, to whom the promiſe is made, may not be baptiſed, there can be no force in the Apoſtles ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are not willing to contend with our opponent, about ſmall matters, to wit, how the Apoſtles counſel or exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Repent and be baptized,</hi> may paſs by the name of a command. But having layd down a truth for the ſubſtance, in what he firſt affirmeth, we ſhall joyn iſſue with him in it. (1) we conſent, that the command to be baptized to parent and child is one. Then what ſaith the comand? <hi>Repent and be baptized:</hi> We an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, What God hath joyned together, let no man put aſunder. The accuſer was telling but now, of an inſeparable connexion: he might have better obſerved it here, then where he ſought it. But (2) Though we approve our accuſer in the firſt part of what he affirms, yet we muſt leave him to himſelf to make good
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152411:23"/>his reaſon, <hi>viz. If any to whom the promiſe is made, may not be baptized, then there is no force in the Apoſtles argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> We make no queſtion, but that, notwithſtanding the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Converts at this Sermon, yet there were very many Jews, to whom this promiſe was made, equally with thoſe that were convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who perſiſted in their obſtinacy; and thereby rendred themſelves and their children incapable of baptiſm, upon the Accuſers own Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples: nevertheleſs, the Argument the Apoſtle made uſe of, was not therefore without force, becauſe they might not be baptized.</p>
            <p>The Accuſer having put an end to the cruel torture, with which he hath racked the Scripture beyond all bounds of ſobriety, he leads you to ſee his fair fruits of better information; where, we believe, you will finde enough to diſcover the perſon's very great want of a ſober Spirit, to ſay no more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the Lord ſatisfied me about Infant-baptiſm: being thus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, I went to hear the publick Miniſtery; but this coming to the ears of the Anabaptiſts, there came three of their Society the nex: day to me, to have an account concerning this thing: I told them, If they would be pleaſed to come at a time appointed, I would give them the Reaſons of my withdrawing from them: and accordingly they came, the Preachers, and Principaleſt among them; where I gave them an account of my withdrawing from them, as many of my Friends can bear me witneſs: which was as followeth: 1. Their denying the Children of Believers a right to the Covenant. 2. Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in conſtant neglect of an Ordinance of Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> ſinging of Pſalms.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus the Lord ſatisfied me,</hi> &amp;c. and in his entrance on this of Baptiſm, he ſaith, <hi>And upon ſerious enquiring into the Word, and earneſt ſeeking of the Lord, it pleaſed him to ſatisſie me;</hi> and a little after, <hi>but by conſidering, I ſaw their miſtakes</hi> &amp;c. If the Accuſer deſerves the praiſe which ſeems deſired by him, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to him, of having, with much ſearch of the Scripture, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and Prayer, ſound out and ſet in order theſe Grounds, wherein his ſatisfaction lay, before he departed from us: would it not ſeem ſomewhat unhandſome dealing, and beneath a learned Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, that above a month after our Accuſels departure from us, theſe, our accuſers meditations, ſhould be publickly preached in that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152411:24"/>Town, in matter and form, well-nigh <hi>verbatim,</hi> as he here hath written them; without acknowledging whoſe Collections they were? but we leave them to agree, whether the one's claim to them in the Pulpit, or the other's in the Preſs, ſhall carry away the applauſe deſired: and go on to conſider, what he Reports of that Meeting, in which he gives account of his with-drawing. The firſt Ground whereof, as he preſents it, we have already tendered to examination. The ſecond is our <hi>living in conſtant neglect of an Ordinance of Chriſt,</hi> viz. <hi>ſinging of Pſalms.</hi> At this Meeting, he charged us, with denying ſinging of Pſalms: now he calls it, living in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant neglect of it. About which, what our Light and Practice is (and as then in effect was ſaid) you may take thus: We do fully and cordially own, ſpeaking to our ſelyes; teaching and admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another in Pſalms, Hymns, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>; ſinging and making Melody with Grace in out heart to the Lord, to be the will of Chriſt; according to which wholy men of God are bound in all generations to ſound forth his high Praiſes in the Church by Jeſus Chriſt: which ought to be performed by them, being merry in the Lord, with Melody in their hearts, and a diſtinct and chearful voice, expreſſed either in the Songs of <hi>Moſes, David;</hi> or otherwiſe, as the Spirit bringeth things to their remembrance, and gives them utterance, to the edification of themſelves and others, that they ſtanding by may ſay <hi>Amen</hi> or <hi>Hallelujah</hi> at ſuch giving of thanks. Unto the performance of which work, although under the ſhadowy diſpenſation, there were added Muſical Inſtruments, and Singers ſpecially appointed to attend that ſervice; which are done away in Chriſt: And although in the beginning of the Goſpels confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſome extraordinary gifs of the Spirit adorned it, which are now ceaſed; yet the ſubſtance of it abides as a duty ſtill in force: to the which, we are not convinced, that the common artificial Rhymes, Meaſures, and Tunes are eſſential. In the practice hereof, according to the meaſure of the Light and Grace of Chriſt, the Churches and Chriſtians accuſed (we truſt) endeavour to be found faithful to the Lord. Although whatever imperfections or defects of this kinde, were apprehended among us by our Accuſer; yet in pretending this neglect of ours, as a juſt ground of his withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from us, he ſhews himſelf to have been a very unfaithful member, while he walked with us, in that he never declared any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence or ſcruple about this matter, until he had thus left us; nor yet
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152411:24"/>of the next thing of which he chargeth us, Thus,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, For neglecting of Family-duty, maintaining it to be a mans liberty, not his duty, to pray in his family.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What our Principles and Practiſes are in this matter, we have hinted before. Touching the later clauſe, which is here told you (but very falſly) to have been then preſented by him, as the ground of his departure: as there is not the leaſt colour, why he ſhould lay it upon the whole Church from whom he withdrew, (much leſs, upon the whole of that people, whom he ſtileth Anabaptiſts;) ſo neither ſeems it ſo honeſtly charged on the perſon, where all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion that we can learn of it, is: the paſſages appear to have been thus: At the time he mentioneth, when ſome Members came to confer with him about the Reaſons of his departure; among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, he gave this for one; becauſe we denied Family-duties. It was replied to this effect: We do not deny it; but do own, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm. That it is the Duty of Parents and Maſters fearing God, to be frequent in calling their Families together, inſtructing them in the Principles of Religion; endeavouring by all means poſſible, their Converſion and Salvation, and in their preſence to ſpread their condition before the Lord; praying for them, that God would ſet home ſuch inſtructions and endeavours with power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But afterward, ſeveral things being debated, a Caſe was put: What and if the Maſter had an ungodly Family, in which he could not judge any one did fear the Lord, with whom he could joyn, as with one Spirit, in Prayer; whether he was bound twice a day, <hi>viz.</hi> Morning and Evening, to joyn in Prayer with them? It was replied by a Brother, That if he ſaw advantage might come to them thereby; and found the Lord making his Spirit free, he might ſo do; it was his liberty: but as to any poſitive command, that did binde him in ſuch caſes, the party thus ſpeaking, ſaid, he knew none. Upon which, one in the company drew this concluſion from theſe words, That we made it a mans liberty, not his duty, to pray in his Family. How fairly this is inferred from what was ſaid; and how righteouſly fathered upon the whole; and how certainly this inſtance was a ground of his leaving us (which himſelf ſaith, was afore this conference) is left to the ſober Chriſtian to judge.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:152411:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, For denying the power of the Magiſtrate for puniſhing evil-doers, (to wit, Quakers.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What the Principles of the people, whom he in the general accuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth are in this point, is full well known to the world, by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of Faith, particularly that of the Congregations in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> Art. 47. the words are theſe, <hi>A civil Magiſtrate is an Ordinance of God ſet up by him for the puniſhment of evil-doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well, and that in all lawful things commanded by them, ſubjection ought to be given by us in the Lord, not only for wrath, but for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake; and that we are to make ſupplication for Kings, and all that are in authority, that under them we may live a quiet and peaceable life, in all godlineſs and honeſty,</hi> Rom. 13. 1 Pet. 2. 1 Tim. 2.</p>
            <p>As for this particular Congregation, they have not onely explicitely teſtified their Fellowſhip, with theſe Churches in this Profeſſion of Faith: but it is well known to the Accuſer, that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Members have, and as occaſion offers, ſtill do addreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Magiſtracy in that place, for their puniſhment and reformation of ſuch diſorders as fall under their Obſervation. Onely they ſay, They are not perſwaded, that the ſword of the Magiſtrate is a mean appointed by Chriſt in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-miniſtration for the puniſhing or reclaiming of an erring or miſ-guided Conſcience, in matters that do depend upon the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Spirit. As for the people mentioned as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, (to wit, the Quakers,) it was affirmed by thoſe Brethren at that Meeting, and ſtill is, that wherein the Quakers ſhould be found to commit any Offence againſt the Rules of good manners, the Magiſtrate hath power as fully to proceed with them, as with any other men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. For ſlighting the publick miniſtry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This charge is left exceeding raw; whether it relate to all the people by him called Anabaptiſts? or to this ſociety in <hi>Tiverton?</hi> or to thoſe members only in particular? whether it be ſlighting a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152411:25"/>publick miniſtry, as not being the ordinance of Chriſt? or whether it being ſome kinde of teſtifying againſt that which is uſually called publick miniſtry? If the latter, then whether it be only that pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick miniſtry in <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rton,</hi> or elſe univerſally? whether it be their perſons, their gift or ſtanding that is ſlghted? here is latitude for the Reader to make conſtruction as he pleaſeth. Our underſtanding in this matter, is, we doe own and honour as an ordinance of Chriſt, a publick ſpiritual miniſtry or ſervice, to be performed to him and his people in the things of the Goſpel, by perſons qualified in ſome good meaſure from the Lord, and called and ſet apart ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Chriſts laws in his Church; both as to that miniſtry of the word of reconciliation, and edification, and to that of ſerving tables. And though this be not as yet fully brought forth and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in that congregation (it being a falſhood in ſcorne caſtion them, that <hi>Willtam Facie</hi> is their Paſtor, if by it be underſtood a man choſen and ordained to that office) as through grace it is with ſome Churches with whom we have communion in the Lord; yet is it that mercy in order to which they are waiting on the Lord for more of his light and ſpirit, in making proof and tryal of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of ſuch among them as they have beſt ground to judg the Lord hath beſtowed moſt of his gifts and graces on for that work. As for the miniſtry of the nation, we have this to ſay. We own and honour many of the men, not only as holy, but as ſuch that have received gifts and graces from the Lord, which he hath bleſſed in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of them. But as for the forme of their ſtanding, as miniſters in office in the Church of Chriſt, we judg it not to be according to the rule of the Scripture. Nevertheleſſe we doe not own nor wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly allow, that in this caſe any ſhould take up railing accuſations, or unſound and unſavoury expreſſions, ſuch as gender to ſtrife ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to godly edifying; but doe pray for, exhort to, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour after this, that our ſpeech might be alwayes with grace, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with ſalt, that we may know how to anſwer every man. If the Accuſer had the knowledg of, and was grieved with any ſuch hard ſpeeches either from the whole or any members, his faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs would have been in exerciſe to have teſtified againſt it in his place, while he had communion with us: his utter ſilence in bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any witneſs of this kinde till now, was it ſeemes from hence, that he knew he was ſecond to none in any language of that nature.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:152411:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I offered to give them a farther account of my withdrawing from the hypocriſy and wickedneſs of one <hi>William Facy,</hi> who is their preſent Paſtor: but they refuſed to heare, and deſired I would not caſt dirt to their face; I deſired that they would pleaſe to give an account, what they had againſt me, but I could get nothing but this from them, <hi>viz.</hi> you are withdrawn from us, and have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected your place among us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this paſſage is all the colour the Accuſer hath for what he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to be one main occaſion of publiſhing his booke <hi>(viz.)</hi> that he could not have liberty to ſpeake for himſelf: which was thus: at this conſerence, wherein his five unrighteous grounds were at large debated, he ſeveral times began to inſiſt on what he calls the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs and hypocriſy of <hi>William Facy,</hi> which now (being at liberty in printing) he diſplays at large. Of which the Reader may in it's place expect an examination.</p>
            <p>The matters he maketh ſo large an outcry of, came to paſs while the Accuſer walked as a member there, who as he was acquainted with the mans ſin and fall, ſo alſo declared himſelf fully ſatisfied with his being humbled in the ſence of it to the duſt, and publickly in the Church, praiſed the Lord for his repentance and recovery. But now beginning to make a narrative of all thoſe matters in the preſence of his other friends, with the ſame rancour of ſpirit, as may be perceived running through his book (it being ſix moneths afore, that he had ſo ſoemnly witneſſed his ſatisfaction in the others repentance) he was deſired to deſiſt from ſo doing, unleſs he had any thing to lay to his charge, either before or ſince thoſe acts, of which the Church had took ſuch publick cogniſance, and had proceeded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him with ſuch ſevere cenſure; but there was nothing of any other kinde could be produced. In that he ſayeth, <hi>I could get nothing but this from them, You are withdrawn from us, and have neglected your place among us.</hi> Theſe brethren came to him not as from the Church, but upon his motion to ſpeake with him; neither was the place or company judged expedient to open what was to be laid to his charge, (beſides, this manifeſt withdrawing of his) it followeth not, that therefore the Church had nothing elſe to charge him with.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:152411:26"/>
            <p>By this time he hath made his report (how righteouſly, let the impartial judg) what principles he found among us. That which remaineth (except here and there a repetition of what hath been ſaid before) is only what carriages and miſcarriages he met with among us, with his obſervations on them, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions to young Chriſtians, &amp;c. from them. All which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of perſonal failings and infirmities (ſhould it be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that they are truth) would not be of that weight upon the deliberated thoughts of the grave and ſpiritually judging man, as that he ſhould hence condemn the profeſſion and way we walk in; unleſs there appeared in the nature thereof, ſomthing of a cauſe producing neceſſarily ſuch effects. To ſuch a one therefore it might ſuffice, beſides the ſtating of our principles, to declare in ſimplicity of heart, as in the preſence of the Lord, that our ſoul loatheth ſuch abominations, in our ſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. But becauſe this remaining part of the engine may do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution upon the ſimple and harmleſs ones, toward whom it is profeſſedly directed, and our God having not left us without boldneſs of appeal to him, &amp; righteous matter for the clearing our ſelves to men, in divers things falſly preſented touching us, we preſume on the readers patience to proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then they ſollicited me again to return to them: but ſeeing they could not prevail, they ſummoned me to appear before them ſuch a day. I told them, that if I might have the liberty to bring ſome friends of mine with me, I would meet with them: this being granted, and the day aſſigned, I deſired</hi> Mr. Forteſcue Lowman, <hi>Miniſter of the word in</hi> Cadlie, <hi>with ſome other friends to be preſent: whom I found very ready, and accordingly at the ſams time appointed, came with me to their meeting where were preſent ſome of the ableſt of that party in theſe parts, both from</hi> Plymouth, Dartmouth, Tornes, Boveytracy, Bampton, <hi>and ſeverall other parts, whom they had invited to aſſiſt them; and it is remarkable to behold, the juſt hand of the Lord, who will not bear with ſin, nor ſuffer his truth to fall to the ground: as ſoon as we came into their meeting, it pleaſed the Lord to ſtrike ſuch a damp upon their ſpirits, and caſt them into ſuch a hurry, that not a man among them would ingage to juſtifie their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, but one</hi> Thomas Glaſs, (<hi>who was not of that ſociety, but a teacher of a company of them at</hi> Boveytracy) <hi>in the name of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152411:27"/>reſt of the</hi> Anabaptiſts, <hi>deſired, that all ſuch as were not members of their ſociety would withdraw. I told them, if my friends ſhould not be preſent with me, according to appointment, I would withdraw alſo (knowing the inconveniency of being with them alone, when there was no one to teſtify the playn truth of things.) He told me, if I would deny the authority of Chriſt and his Church, I might: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom I replyed, That the authority of Chriſt, I did own; but your authority I did deny.</hi> William Facy <hi>not willing to be laid o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, joyned with this motion, and deſired my friends to withdraw. Then</hi> Mr. Lowman <hi>told them, he had ſomthing to propoſe to them before he did withdraw, if they pleaſed:</hi> Thomas Glaſs <hi>replyed, Pray withdraw, for you have nothing to doe here. So we withdrew, and one of my friends ſaid, Report no more that we reſuſe to give you a meeting; which falſe report they have often ſpread to deceive the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to carry on their deſign, by perſwading the ignorant into an opinion, that ſuch as differ from them have nothing to ſay from Gods word, to juſtifie their practiſe. The ſame night came</hi> Thom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Glaſs <hi>(it is worth inquiring why they ſent not their Paſtor</hi> William Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>if they were not aſhamed of him, or he to look on me) and one of his brethren to my houſe, with a meſſage from the reſt of the</hi> Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, <hi>to declare that they had rejected me.</hi> Mr. Lowman <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent, deſired to know, by what rules they walked, to reject a man, for withdrawing upon ſuch juſt and reaſonable grounds, as I had before urged. But</hi> Thomas Glaſs <hi>refuſed to entertain any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with him for his ſatisfaction; and told him they had nothing to doe with him. And being asked why they denyed my friends li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to be preſent in their meeting, according to appointment, and refuſed to give</hi> Mr. Lowman <hi>liberty to propoſe what he had to offer them:</hi> Thomas Glaſs <hi>brake out in a pettiſh fit, ſaying, that we had attempted to diſturb them in the worſhip of God; and charged us with abuſing the Name of God, and his people, with incivility, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſty, and want of knowledge; and withall affirmed, that he was imployed by the reſt of his brethren to tell us ſo: Unto which</hi> Mr. Lowman <hi>replyed, If you are imployed by your brethren to give us ſuch language, pray be pleaſed to returne this meſſage again, that I humbly conceive, they have done us the wrong, to appoint ſuch a meeting with us; and when we came, to deny us our liberty to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and now to ſend ſuch language after us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>We did not diſturb you in your worſhip of God, for we did nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152411:27"/>ſee nor heare you about any religious exerciſe when we came, neither did we ſpeake a word till you bid us depart, neither were uncivil with you, for we withdrew according to your deſire.</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Glaſs <hi>being deſired to ſhew ſome reaſon, for giving ſuch ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous words, replyed, That he was not come to diſpute, but declare in the name of their Church, that he had rejected me, the partiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of my charge, were as followeth.</hi> (1) <hi>That I had withdrawn from their ſociety, and neglected my place amongſt them.</hi> (2.) <hi>That I had vilified ſome of their brethren, whom I had forgiven.</hi> (3.) <hi>That I had viliſied ſome of their brethren for denying Magiſtracy, neglect of Family duties, ſinging of Pſalmes.</hi> (4) <hi>That I had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed my Father in Law. Theſe things put together,</hi> Thomas Glaſs, <hi>and one more of his brethren, did in the name of the Church, declare me guilty of blaſphemy (you may judge this was a learned aſſembly, that brought this charge to ſuch a concluſion) and they were ſent to tell me they had rejected me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you have at large his ſtory of the Churches proceedings with him (for hitherto was onely the private advice and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors of particular brethren) in which he layes before his ignorant young Chriſtian, ſeveral things, though with ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, as may, if need be, afford him ſome retreat; yet in ſuch a way, as may eaſily beget a perſwaſion, and hath done ſo in many, that he intendeth they ſhould beleeve theſe things in it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Church had granted a meeting, and aſſigned a day, wherein <hi>Mr. Lowman,</hi> and others ſhould propoſe in way of diſcourſe, what they had to ſay in examination of our proceeedings; which when they came to doe, was denyed them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in order to this, the Church had invited to aſſiſt them, ſome great number of the ableſt of our party that could be got in the ſeveral quarters of Country, far and neer, who were then preſent.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That at <hi>Mr. Lowmans</hi> approach, they all were ſtricken in ſuch a damp and burry by a juſt hand of God, that no one durſt engage to juſtifie their proceedings.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the Accuſer was judged an offender, and we would not give him liberty to ſpeak for himſelf.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:152411:28"/>5. That this learned aſſembly (as he cals them) brought his charge to this concluſion, that he was guilty of blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That this aſſembly imployed meſſengers to charge him, <hi>Mr. Lowman</hi> and others, with abuſing the name of God and his people, with incivility, diſhoneſty, and want of knowledge, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>At moſt of this affair, our ſelves (that publiſh this) being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, we can upon knowledge teſtifie the falſhood of theſe things ſuggeſted. All we ſhall do, to maniſeſt the abuſe impoſed on the unwary Reader, will be, to give this true, brief account of the thing.</p>
            <p>The accuſer having dealt ſo unworthily with thoſe that had endeavoured more particularly his conviction; the Church at length ſent ſome meſſengers to ſignifie, that they expected him at their meeting ſuch a day: To whom he replyed, he would not come, unleſs he might bring ſome friends with him. That theſe meſſengers withſtood not his declared reſolution, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gave way to it, as their particular opinion that it might be granted him, this is not denyed; but that the Church gave a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch inſtruction, or allowance, is not ſo. At that time there were four brethren of other congregations (and not one more) having agreed among themſelves ſeveral dayes before, to be about that Country, and to give that Church a viſit, who by providence were brought thither, not knowing any thing more or leſs of their expecting the Accuſer that day before them, much leſs of <hi>Mr. Lowmans</hi> coming to propoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing; nor were they ſent for by the Church, nor did the Church as we ſuppoſe, know any thing of the intended viſit, till after the day that he was ſummoned (as he cals it) and had took hold of the ſeeming conceſſion, and given out, he would bring <hi>Mr. Lowman,</hi> &amp;c. We being preſent, the Congregation deſired us to aſſiſt them that day, being the uſual day of the week that they met on, which we were ready to do according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and having ſpent ſome hours together in prayer and exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, about noon-time took the Accuſers caſe into conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with the rumor that was ſpread in the Town of a diſpute that was to proceed, &amp;c. Upon which enquiring, and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evident, that the Church gave them that had been their
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152411:28"/>meſſengers no ſuch allowance, as they had given way unto; as alſo weighing how little it could be hoped that we ſhould adminiſter conviction to the Accuſer, when ſuch a rabble of people as were at the door, would thruſt in about us and him; and withal, having other matters to charge him with, that were not convenient to be declared before them.</p>
            <p>Moreover, that a true taſte could not be had of the mans ſpirit; and what himſelf might be conſcientiouſly perſwaded of, and upon what grounds, if the matter ſhould be taken up, and the time ſpent by any others on his half: on theſe and ſome other grounds it was agreed, we would deſire any that ſhould come in with him, not being members, to withdraw; and withal, the members wereexhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that in caſe the rude concourſe of people ſhould throng in with him (which indeed proved ſo) to abide in their places in the feare of the Lord, and not make themſelves acceſſarie to any confuſion, though tempted and provoked ſo to be, by the multitude. Our Brother <hi>Glaſs</hi> alſo was pitcht upon to ſpeake the ſence of the whole; firſt, to the multitude, in caſe they ſhould throng in, deſiring we might enjoy our liberty to be private by our ſelves, there being nothing to be debated that concerned them: and then to the Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, to lay before him thoſe evils which he was to be charged with, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the proofs we had of them, and to heare what he had to offer touching it, &amp;c. Then was he ſent for, who brought in with him, and after him, ſuch a multitude as hath been declared, who ruſhing in with no ſmall incivility, as is uſual where-ever ſuch contentions are expected, the members generally ſate ſilent as was deſired, though grieved to ſee ſuch provoking demeanour: which the Accuſer calleth a juſt hand of the Lord, ſtriking a dampe on our ſpirits, but we take to be a mercy, and token of love, to be kept ſerious and ſilent under ſuch incivilities. Then did our Brother <hi>Glaſs</hi> deſire ſuch as were not members to withdraw, &amp;c. whereat, thoſe he calls his friends appearing to be troubled at the diſappointment of their deſigne (which it ſeemes was, as ſome of that party have given our, mainly to have thrown in our faces the paſſages about <hi>William Facy</hi>) many diſcontented words dropt from ſeveral of them; to whom the anſwer was, Our continued deſires were, they would not deale uncivilly with us, but afford us our liberty, being we had no buſineſs in hand that concerned them. It is like that if <hi>Mr. Lowman</hi> made any motion to ſpeak among the reſt, he had
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152411:29"/>the ſame anſwer. The Accuſer, to ſhew his valour in refelling any manner of adviſe or admonition, refuſed to abide, though again and again exhorted to it, except the company he brought with him might remaine; ſpeaking reprochfully of any authority of Chriſt among us, and with much deriſiont at length he with them withdrew. (At this time then, he being ſo often admoniſhed to remaine, was not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred his liberty to ſpeake for himſelf. The Church then conſidered what was their duty farther concerning him, reſolved to ſend meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers again to him, of whom they thought good our Brother <hi>Glaſs</hi> ſhould be one, he being acquainted with him, and might beſt work on him; who in much meekneſs and bowels deſired him to come to the Church, and heare what they had to offer to him, promiſing him what liberty he could deſire toward the clearing himſelf; but he utterly refuſed to come, going on to ſpeak contemptuouſly, as his uſual manner of late had been, not only of the Church, but of the way it ſelf, &amp;c. This anſwer was returned to us (and may it not be worth noting by the way, that he makes no mention of this meſſage wherein he was again offered liberty to ſpeake for himſelf, but ſtill refuſed it) the Church then conſidering again the nature of the evils they had in charge againſt him (of which hereafter) as alſo the irreconcileable enmity that he manifeſted towards us, and the way we walke in; that we were out of any capacity to endeavour farther his recovery, or to deliver him from thoſe iniquities that he boaſted in as his glory, concluded it our duty to cut him off, and reject him from the fellowſhip of this body. But there was not (that we remember) the leaſt mention made of the word blaſpemie, much leſs was his charge ſummed up under that denomination, or or brought to that concluſion by that learned aſſembly, as he is pleaſed in deriſion to call us.</p>
            <p>As to the occurreaces about the delivering the knowledge of our proceedings to him, however we are ſatisfied, and could make it out upon good demonſtration, that it holds proportion with the reſt of his book, both for the forging lies, and miſrepreſenting what hath any colour of truth in it; yet we judge it not worth the while to cumber our preſent work, or the Reader withal, it appearing at beſt, but an envious paraphraſt on the weakneſs of a particular man, thereby to aſperſe the way he walketh in, and the whole people he walketh with. The ſlanders therein may be more conveniently diſproved and reproved if need be face to face. Onely the Reader
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152411:29"/>may know, that what paſſages were betwixt our Brother <hi>Glaſs,</hi> and them, about their uncivility <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it appears, that as they were not any part of our Meſſage, ſo neither were they affirmed by him to have been; but delivered by him in the midſt of much diſcourſe, as his own obſervation: at the ſight whereof, as he had cauſe to be grieved, ſo having ſuch an opportunity, might juſtly complain of. As for that alſo about Blaſphemy, as we are abuſed by them in it, ſo is our Brothers the occaſion pretended to give colour to it being only thus: Our Brother <hi>Glaſs,</hi> being come to him with the Meſſage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boveſaid, began in ſome freeneſs of ſpeech, (as far as the Accuſer's and Mr. <hi>Lowman</hi> 's interpoſitions<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and interruptions would give leave) to ſet before the young man his ſtate, manifeſting; with what tenderneſs we had demeaned our ſelves from time to time toward him, being alwayes ready to counſel and admoniſh him: but he had perſiſted, notwithſtanding all means uſed, ſlighting our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, deſpiſing our reproofs, ſtill oppoſing, contradicting, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming. At this word, Mr. <hi>Lowman,</hi> as was his manner, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, Will you tharge him with blaſphemy? yea, you charge him with blaſphemy: how will you make good your charge of blaſphemy? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though it was anſwered, as both the brethren teſtifie, That this Expreſſion was not the Churches, but out bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threr's own Affirontion of him, which he was ready to make good, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rward the conſer ſaith <hi>[He had made ſad ſhifts te mince the matter]</hi> ſurely, needed not to be ſo put to it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an ear-witneſs to thoſe unparaſleld reproaches, that by him, and by means of him, were caſt upon the way and people of the Lord, which the Spirit of the Lord doth not unuſually call by that very name, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.6. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.4. though rendered in our Tranſlation, <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aming, evil ſpeaking, ſlanderouſly reperting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that you may ſee the irregular Proceedings of ſuch as pretend to Religion, and under that pretence draw away many poor ſouls from thoſe means which God hath bleſſed for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion and edification; to the end, ſuch may be warned to take heed, Give me leave to anſwer to my Charge, and I ſhall ſpeak nothing but the plain truth; and let the moderate judge, where the guilt lies. For the firſt particular of my Charge for withdrawing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152411:30"/>from them: I judge it a great bleſſing, that the Lord hath ſo far opened my eyes, as to bring me out from among them: which will eaſily appear, if you remember the grounds I have already alledged, and ſhall yet urge, as well from their wickedneſs of Practice, as Principles, that I found among them; inſomuch, that I wonder how the ſober among them, could walk with them hitherto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here he takes on him to anſwer to the particulars of his Charge, as himſelf ſhapes them, after a ſharp invective, of which his Book is full; and from which our God, to whom we have committed our Cauſe. will deliver us: [<hi>For the firſt particular of my Charge for withdrawing from them, I judge it a great bleſſing,</hi> &amp;c.] This indeed was one thing, which, had he abode, we ſhould have laid the evil of before him, that notwithſtanding when he crept in among us, under a profeſſion, that in the fear of the Lord, in conſcience and judgement, he did put on Chriſt; and lifted up his hand to the moſt High God, that he would walk among us, according to Grace re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, as a Member in the Body of Chriſts that he did yet, contrary to the Law of his Relation, without any endeavours to make the Church ſenſible of any evil, either in Principles or Practice, or to help on their reformation; wholly deſert them, and withdraw from them: this he counteth his great bleſſing on the grounds al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged: to which we ſay, That this our Defence conſidered, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the true taſte of his Spirit from firſt to laſt, the Moderate to whom he appeals, may eaſily judge the greater Bleſſing to be on our hand, that we are delivered from ſuch a one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this I ſhall ſhew you in anſwer to the ſecond Branch of my Charge, which is a vilifying ſome members, which they ſay, I have forgiven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was alſo an evil which we ſhould have laid before him, That he (as all the Members did one by one) explicitely witneſſed his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſatisfied in the repentance of a ſinner under cenſure; and withal, ſolemnly gave publick thanks to the Lord, for having thus humbled and healed him, as alſo forgiving him freely, in the Name of the Lord; and joyning in the receiving him into Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as a Member of the Body again; he yet ſhould at length, after above half a yee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſilence, and declared ſatisfaction, diſplay all the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152411:30"/>repented-of evils of this perſon with wherever aggravations and addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he could, to render him, and the people he walked with, odious to perſons oppoſite to the way of the Lord we walk in both prophane and profeſſors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The occaſion of this charge they bring againſt me, is as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:</hi> William Facy, <hi>their preſent Paſtor walked ſo diſorderly, his wickedneſs was ſo great, that they could do no leſs then ſuſpend him; but ſo ſlightly did they deal in the buſineſs that his ſuſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pretended repentance, and admiſſion again, was all within one week. Shortly after, he feigned himſelf mad, and began to play pranks with his wife: called a for baſon to let out his blood; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that he would cut his Throat: goes to caſt his child into the fire, which child ſhortly after ſickned and died. Much of this, I was both an eye and ear-witneſs unto: for his wife came crying unto me that ſhe was afraid to abide with him in the houſe: gave me a relation of thoſe things; deſiring me to come with her to her husband. When I came, I found him on the bed: I asked him how he did; but he gave me no anſwer. After ſome time I had been there, he aroſe, and goes from his houſe. This wickedneſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by him was deemed then by the Anabaptiſts (as was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by himſelf acknowledged) to be out of a deſign to get ſome mony from his wife, having married a widow, which kept certain Bills or Bonds of Debt in ſome Friends hands, leſt he ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it: for which the Anabaptiſts ſuſpended him again; and in a little time received him again; wherein I was never ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to this day: and in teſtimony of my diſſatisfaction, I refuſed to ſit down with them at the Lords Table ever ſince. Now they charge me for vilifying ſome of their members, when I ſpake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the plain truth, in declaring againſt their ſin; and they ſay, I have forgiven him, when I was thus unſatisfied in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and now judge it but feigned: for he that could ſo ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificially counterfeit madneſs, could eaſily counterfeit ſadneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here he begins to entertain the Reader, with whatſoever new or old, before or ſince his rejection, he can invent and vent againſt this <hi>William Facy;</hi> all which, leſt it ſhould ſeem no otherways in the Readers eye, then the perſonal failings of a poor frail man, and not to be reaſonably imputed to the cauſe or people he walks with, and therefore no juſt ground for his reproaching and forſaking them; he
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152411:31"/>pins it upon the whole, by inculcating ſeveral times a falſhood, as the running verſe of his diſtinct Paragraphs, <hi>[yet they continue him to be their Paſtor,]</hi> and at length, cloſeth up the whole with this, <hi>[—whether I have cauſe to withdraw, where ſuch iniquity is indulged.]</hi> In this the Accuſer, as in his former ſtory, about the Churches rejecting him, expoſeth the Reader to a tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuppoſing theſe things to be a very truth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Church dealt ſlightly, and ſhort of their duty with <hi>William Facy,</hi> on his firſt evil.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Accuſer himſelf was an eye and ear-witneſs to the pranks he played (to uſe his own words) when he feigned himſelf mad, called for a baſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Anabaptiſts judged, and himſelf confeſſed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that he feigned himſelf mad, out of a deſign to get ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That the Church indulged this iniquity, and ſo they had done the former, onely ſuſpending, and in a very little time receiving him again.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That this Accuſer was all along unſatisfied with his repentance, as being artificially counterfeited.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That upon the whole, himſelf is not to be accounted one that vilifieth his brethren, in that he ſpake nothing but plain truth in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring againſt the others ſin.</p>
            <p>To free ſuch as deſire to know the truth of things from the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer's ſnare, we ſhall only preſent this ſhort account.</p>
            <p>This poor Creature now under accuſation having walked blameleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (as far as we could judge) ſeveral yeers among this people, in the faithful and diligent improvement of a good gift of Grace, to preach Chriſt's Goſpel, that the Lord had bleſſed him with, and bleſſed in his hand, both to converſion and edification, was at length over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by the power of temptation ariſing from ſome more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary croſſes, in a ſtate of Marriage, whereinto he was newly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered; wherein he (as alſo his yoke-fellow) was attended with tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als exceeding bitter to be born: which yet, for honor of Truths ſake, he greatly concealed. On a time, being overwhelmed with grief and impatience, he rent a Garment that was in his hand; and uſed ſome expreſſions to his VVife, that ſavoured of a very diſturbed and paſſionate frame of Spirit: of which ſhe complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſome Members, and it coming to the knowledge of the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152411:31"/>Church, they required the ceſſation of his exerciſing his gift publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, till they might be ſatisfied of his repentance for ſuch iniquity; which he tendring the knowledg of abundantly, within a ſhort time (as the Accuſer ſayes) they accepted of his miniſtring to them again as formerly.</p>
            <p>Some time after which, the cauſe of his griefe remaining unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, exceeding bitter and little hopes appearing to him that it could be taken away, that alſo which the Accuſer mentioneth about writings being ſome aggravation of his trouble; It pleaſed the Lord to let out the Tempter, to tempt him to that extreamity, that upon a freſh onſet of the enemy of his peace, he brake out in his wives preſence (none but ſhee being with him) into a condition as a man for the time beteaved of the uſe of his reaſon, in words not unlike his, <hi>Job</hi> 7.15, 16. As if he had choſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n preſent death, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then life, and could have helped it on with his own hands; and had deſired the ſame for his little one, which had been maimed and ſickly before, and was now weake in the ſickneſs of which it ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after died, being an impoſthumation that brake within it.</p>
            <p>Of all which, together with the aggravations of it, what breakings it hath been to his bones, to the enfeebling his very outward man; what teares, what wounds it hath begotten in him and all that were round about him, That the Lord ſhould be thus diſhonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the fear of God ſhould no more rule in his heart, it is not unknown to the Accuſers conſcience, but our comfort is, that our God knoweth how loathſom the thoughts of the iniquity were to us, and with what impartiality, deteſtation, and ſeverity we have borne our proteſt againſt it, and with what heart-bleedings we doe think of it to this very day. In teſtimony whereof, he himſelf was ſometime ſince drawing, and was taking advice with ſeveral (long before this pamphlet was out) about the publiſhing a narrative of the whole; ſhewing the inward declenſions that at firſt ſecretly took hold of him in point of his communion with God, the various temptations that then attended him, the great iniquities that at length got victory ever him, with their aggravations, the Churches faithful and thorow dealing with him, and the foorſteps of God rebuking, ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſing, yea breaking him to peeces; and yet the ſweet a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d kindely operation of his hand, ſuſtaining him in diſtreſſes from ſinking in diſpaire, and at length bringing him forth to ſee the light of his countenance in the face of Jeſus Chriſt. But the publiſhing
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152411:32"/>this (intended for a warning to them that think they ſtand) was not by ſome at that time thought expedient.</p>
            <p>The Accuſers pretended knowledg of theſe paſſages as an eye and ear-witneſs was no otherwiſe then thus, as himſelf declareth; that when the ſury of the temptation was over, he came in at his wifes deſire, and found him ſilent upon his bed, from whence after ſome time he aroſe, and went out of doors, which was all the iniquity that he ſaw, only he heard his wife make relation of the things to him, but that alſo ſhee did to others afterward; (might not they then be ſayd with as much truth to be eye and eare-witneſſes as he?) When this was ſpread before the Church, in all the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of it, both when they were alone, and when they had obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the aſſiſtance of other congregations for advice, which was very ſuddenly upon it: The Lord knoweth, and the conſcience of this Accuſer knoweth, what dayes of anguiſh and ſorrow they were to us all, who forthwith not only ſuſpended him again (as he calls it) from the publick exerciſe of his gift, but withdrew our communion from him in all the ordinances of Chriſt, that hold out the peculiar fellowſhip of the Saints, notwithſtanding he then teſtified, how the very morning after his iniquity the Lord had broken him for it, and with many meltings he declared it: inſomuch as though the whole could not but have compaſſion on his miſery, knowing the unſpeakable diſtreſſe of ſpirit he was under while the temptation was upon him (and therefore were far from judging that he feigned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf mad, but rather that ſuffering ſuch terrours, he was even diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.15.) yet knowing how the name of the Lord was blaſphemed, and ſeeing that Scripture <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.10. verified in ſome from whom better things were expected, and conſidering how grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly ſuch impatient turnings from the Lord were aggravated in him, who had ſpoken ſo long and openly in his name; The Church judged they were bound to wait on the Lord in ſeparating him from the congregation for ſome conſiderable time, to ſee what fruite would farther demonſtrate his repentance to be ſuch as was not to be repented off. And therefore though during this cenſure he ſeveral times addreſſed himſelf to the Church, tendering ſtill the knowledg of the Lords going on to humble and abaſe him for his iniquity to the duſt, and many feared he would be ſwallowed up with over-much heavineſs, yet held they him under that excluſion from memberſhip, from the third day of the twelfth month, 1655.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152411:32"/>(when he was withdrawn from) till the 12 day of the 4 month 1656. and from thence till the 28 day of the 10 month following, they imployed him not fully to miniſter in all the ordinances of Chriſt as formerly. At that time mentioned, the 12 of the 4 month, the Church received him again as a member, when each member, (and the Accuſer particularly for himſelf, as hath been ſaid) wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed full ſatisfaction in the truth of his repentance, and renewed their love to him. And whereas the Accuſer ſaith, that in teſtimony of diſſatisfaction at him, he never ſate down with them afterward at the Lords table; it is not denyed, but that about that time, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, the Accuſer grew remiſſe and negligent in that, as he did in all other acts of viſible fellowſhip with God; confeſſing but a little before his departure, that the world and relations had drawn him aſide; but that he did abſtaine from the Lords table as a teſtimony againſt any counterfeiting either madneſs or repentance; he never ſpake in the leaſt, as can be found, to any member.</p>
            <p>Whether therefore the Accuſer was not juſtly chargeable with evill, for running up and down, diſplaying all that he could finde againſt this member, himſelf having teſtified ſo amply his ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in his repentance, after the Church had witneſſed ſo faithfully againſt his ſin, and this on purpoſe to render him and the Church odious, as indulging ſuch iniquity, let the ſincere judge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. He cryes down the publick miniſtry for taking of Tythes, when as ſhortly after that his brethren had admitted him to their communion and fellowſhip, he tells them, that unleſs they would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage to him 30 pounds by the year, he would leave them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two things the ignorant young Chriſtian is invited to take up from this ſhort accuſation for truth. Firſt, that this man did at leaſt eſſay to indent with his brethren for 30 l. <hi>per an.</hi> or elſe would leave them. Secondly, that his ſo doing doeth juſtifie the national miniſtry in their taking Tythes, or at leaſt condemneth him for teſtifying againſt it. The whole truth of the former appeareth to have been thus; that a member ſpeaking to him, at a time, about his being fully ſet apart from other imployment to the work of the miniſtry by the Church; he replyed to this effect, that he thought he ſhould not yeild to it, for that he ſhould expect a greater main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, then that Church could well provide for him (as the caſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152411:33"/>ſtood with them) which, ſaid he, cannot be leſs then 30 <hi>l. per annum:</hi> but ſpake nothing of his leaving them.</p>
            <p>This Member having occaſion to ſpeak ſomething concerning him to the Church, related this paſſage, which he (being preſent) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged was from a temptation. But put the caſe he had made this reaſonable Propoſal, it had in the whole amounted to thus much: A Paſtor of a Church (as he is called) having a family, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the flock of Chriſt, to whoſe ſervice he is called, 30 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> as that, ſhort of which he cannot, with his family ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt among them. If this motion be juſtifiable, then the Miniſtery of this Nation muſt not be teſtified againſt, for compelling by Law their Tythes and large Revenues, from perſons whom they judge were never fitted by the Lord for Communion as a Church in all the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of the Goſpel: this is one of the Accuſer's rational infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>He is a notorious lyer, that makes little conſcience of his word, and hath reported many untruths touching the publick Miniſters of</hi> Tiverton; <hi>nay, juſtifieth himſelf in lyes when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved. There was a young man who wrote notes after Mr.</hi> Lowman <hi>preaching upon the Doctrine of the Covenant in</hi> Tiver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton: <hi>which notes this young man delivered to one of the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, who gave them to</hi> William Facy. <hi>Within three or four days after, this young man came to</hi> William Facy, <hi>and demanded theſe Notes: which he plainly and preſumptuouſly denies, ſaying, he had them not: but</hi> William Facy <hi>withdrawing the room the young man eſpies theſe Notes on the Table and takes them into his hand:</hi> VVilliam Facy <hi>comes in; and perceiving the Notes in his hand, takes the Notes by force out of his hand. When the young man reported this to ſome of his Friends,</hi> VVilliam Facy <hi>comes to this young man, and calls him Lyer, before his Maſter, (the young man being then a Servant:) but the young man produced another to teſtifie the truth of this matter, who was with him at</hi> William Facy<hi>'s Houſe, and heard him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Sermon-Notes. Afterward Mr.</hi> Lowman, <hi>meeting with</hi> William Facy, <hi>reproved him for lying:</hi> William Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>to juſtifie himſelf, tells Mr.</hi> Lowman, <hi>That the young man had cleared him in this matter, before his Maſter: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing examined was found a Lye. So here were three lyes:</hi> 1. <hi>he
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152411:33"/>denies the Notes:</hi> 2. <hi>he denies that he did deny them:</hi> 3. <hi>he affirms that the young man had cleared him: which were all falſe. Several untruths hath</hi> William Facy <hi>reported, which upon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination hath plainly and clearly appeared ſo to be: yet they continue him to be their Paſtor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who would not think by what is ſaid, but, 1. That the Accuſer had from hence a very good ground to leave us, or at leaſt a very good evidence to clear himſelf from our ſecond head of matter in charge againſt him, could he have obtained liberty to ſpeak for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? 2. That this <hi>William Facy</hi> hath very many times, been had upon examination, about notorious lyes, touching the Miniſters in <hi>Tiverton,</hi> and otherwiſe; and juſtifies himſelf, when convicted. 3. That he was unqueſtionably found in three in one matter. The deceit of the former inſinuation appears by this, That whatever is pretended to made out in this his ample ſtory, was all tranſacted ſince the time that the Accuſer left us, and was rejected by us; and therefore came too late for his juſt vindication, in the matter for which the Church proceeded with him: but ſtill ſhews him to be as the raging Sea that cannot reſt, whoſe waters caſt up mire and dirt. For the ſecond thing ſuggeſted, if the ſingle affirmations of ſuch a ſlanderous perſon, without any particular inſtances or further proof, ſhall have any weight with the ſober to faſten ſuch charges, then how can the very generation of the Juſt ſtand, in man's day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore envy? Reaſon will prompt the indifferent Reader to ſuppoſe, that were there indeed at hand, proofs ſo cleer upon examination of thoſe horrible impieties and injuries done the Miniſters of <hi>Tiver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> we ſhould have had them inſerted, as more pregnant to his buſineſs, and notorious then this of the Lad's; that the Reader is at large informed in: which upon the beſt light we can obtain, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to no more then this: There was a Sermon it ſeems preach'd in <hi>Tiverton,</hi> about Infants right to the Covenant, which had a very great ſimilitude to, and agreement (to ſay no more) both in matter and form with the Accuſers formerly digeſted and much ſtudied me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations on the ſame ſubject above examined. The Notes of this Sermon, were by a Member (with Mr. <hi>Lowman's</hi> conſent) delivered to the perſon accuſed, and he engaged to deliver them into that Members hand again, as purpoſing to give ſome Animadverſions on them.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:152411:34"/>
            <p>Very ſhortly there came two youths to his houſe, neither of them known to him by face; one of which demanded ſuch notes from him, as being his. <hi>William Facy</hi> denyed the giving them to him, told him he could not have them; the lads importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty grew ſo great upon him, as would admit neither of denyal or delay: at length, not remembring where he had layd them, and (as the lad ſayth) ſaying, he had them not at preſent: while he went into a chamber to ſeek them, the lad found them among other papers on the table: when the youths were gone, they reported, that he had ſaid, he had them not in his houſe at preſent: about which when the youth that claimed them, was examined before his Mr. after he was in two or twree tales, as his Mr. ſtill acknowledgeth, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed it lately in one of our hearing (who publiſh this) as well as before other witneſſes. The ſum is, put caſe <hi>William Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> as the lad reporteth, did ſay, <hi>he had them not at preſent,</hi> therby intending, <hi>he had them not at hand,</hi> nor remembred where to finde them <hi>at preſent;</hi> and the Lad underſtood, he meant by the words, that <hi>he had them not in the houſe at preſent:</hi> If there be not left in the reaſon of men, or love of Chriſt, a way for the ſerious reader to reconcile theſe things, without our farther en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging, or to accommodate them to a more charitable conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and concluſion, then the Accuſer doth, the buſineſs ſhal be left to his cenſure. Only let it be underſtood, to be far from us to excuſe or plead for a willing uſe of ſuch equivocal terms in any caſes, as may leave the party to whom we expreſs our minds un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a temptation, to ſuppoſe otherwiſe then in the plaineſt ſence ſeems to be intended: and we have good ground to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, our accuſed friend was not at this time under this temptation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet they themſelves have given it under their hands, that he is not fit to manage a diſcourſe to vindicate their practiſe and way, in which they now walk; for there was a diſpute appointed betwixt</hi> Mr. Lowman, <hi>and</hi> Mr. William Facy, <hi>which was occaſioned by ſome oppoſition from the</hi> Anabaptiſts <hi>in</hi> Bampton, <hi>where</hi> William Facy <hi>and his followers came and oppoſed</hi> Mr. Lowman <hi>in the Pulpit, who entertained ſome diſcourſe with him before the congregation, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152411:34"/>then referred it to a day of publick diſpute. The Queſtion to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated, was;</hi> Whether the infants of beleevers were in covenant: <hi>But</hi> Mr. William Facy <hi>being deſirous to new ſtate the queſtion, came to</hi> Mr. Lowmans <hi>houſe, and in the preſence of ſeveral, ſwore upon the faith of a Chriſtian, that the queſtion to be diſcourſed, was not</hi> whether infants were in Covenant, <hi>but,</hi> whether infants were to be baptized: <hi>where you may ſee, that ſuch as make little conſcience what they ſay, will make little conſcience what they ſwear.</hi> Mr. Lowman <hi>reproving him for ſwearing told him, that the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be diſcourſed, ſhould be given under each others hand, and if he deſired to have the queſtion ſo ſtated, it ſhould be done; the time and place was appointed, the queſtion ſtated, given in writing; the</hi> Anabaptiſts <hi>willing to wave the buſineſs, imployed a modeſt man of their own party, one</hi> Mr. Nathaniel Strange, <hi>with ſome others of their brethren, of which</hi> Thomas Glaſs <hi>was one, to come and treat with</hi> Mr. Lowman, <hi>in order to wave the diſpute:</hi> Mr. Lowman <hi>deſired to know the reaſon of their retreat: they told him, becauſe</hi> William Facy <hi>was uncapable to manage ſuch an undertaking.</hi> Mr. Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>asked, if they would give it under their hands: which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly they did, and ſubſcribed it in the name of the reſt of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, upon which the diſpute was prevented, yet notwithſtanding</hi> Mr. William Facy <hi>is their Paſtor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being led back again to a ſtory in 1655. by it his ignorant young Chriſtian is expoſed, if he be diſpoſed, to beleeve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That though the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> hold this <hi>William Facy</hi> fit enough to be their Paſtor, yet they have given under their hand, that he is not fit to manage a diſcourſe to vindicate their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe and way.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he is an open ſwearer, and further diſcovered to be a lyar.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> (a feeble flock) were ſorely put to a very ſhamefull retreat from an appointed diſputation with <hi>Mr. Lowman,</hi> and ſo a great advantage on <hi>Mr. Lowmans</hi> ſide was prevented.</p>
            <p>This publick examination of <hi>Mr. Lowman</hi> at <hi>Bampton,</hi> occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by ſome very terrible flouriſhes he had made a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in his preaching upon the point of infant-baptiſm, drew on the appointing a further day for a publick diſpute: in which
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152411:35"/>hurry, the queſtion was not ſo clearly and diſtinctly ſtated, to the apprehenſion of either, but that each (while he thought he took, it ſeems) miſtook the others meaning, and reported va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly; hence was the meeting at <hi>Mr. Lowmans</hi> houſe, to find out and rectifie the miſtake; where the conference was mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with much confidence and ſeeming aſſurance, that the one, and that the other was in the right, though in this variety; ſo that meekneſs and moderation was not called for, between them; neither could ordinarily, yea and nay, goe but a little way: being both in this heat, its poſſible <hi>William Facy</hi> averred it, in the faith of a Chriſtian. Of this, they that are quick at the obſervation of our failings, give teſtimony, and that <hi>Mr. Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> reproved it: undoubtedly if this were done vainly and raſhly, and not in judgment, truth and righteouſneſs, it was an evil worthy to be reproved, and the Lord will humble him in the ſence of it; but the Accuſers Paraphraſt on it muſt paſs as an inference of his own violence, which we leave with his other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to the Lord. Well, the queſtion was agreed unto in writing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the interval (for there was ſome long time ſet till the diſpute ſhould be) it pleaſed the Lord, for our and his hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, to let that forementioned great iniquity of his to break out upon him, whereupon the Church, as hath been ſaid, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt him, ſuſpended him from the exerciſe of his gift in any publick ſervice, denying him alſo communion in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; by means whereof they were (and well might be) at a loſs about the manner of carrying on the appointed diſputation, which either he muſt be left to manage alone without any countenance or conjunction of theirs, or elſe ſome other by <hi>Mr. Lowmans</hi> conſent muſt ſupply his place in that appointment, or otherwiſe ſome way of treaty for the ceſſation of it for the time. The former could not be thought any way expedient, and therefore two or three brethen were deſired to confer with <hi>Mr. Lowman,</hi> either about exchanging his antagoniſt, or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the diſpute for the time: the reſult of which modeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, was the mutual ſubſcription of the inwritten paper.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whereas there was intended a diſpute betwixt</hi> Mr Lowman <hi>and</hi> Mr. Facy, <hi>it is upon ſome weighty conſiderations diſappointed, and broken off.</hi> (1) <hi>We doe not eye it as the work of our day, to permit the work of the Lord to ceaſe, while we leave it, and ſpend our time in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152411:35"/>that which is like to turn to ſo little account.</hi> (2.) Mr. Facy <hi>through ſome more then ordinary providence, is for preſent rendred utterly uncapable for ſuch an undertaking.</hi> 3. <hi>Yet it hath been offered, that our retreat in this may be without manifeſt diſadvantage upon the cauſe and truth of Chriſt, that if</hi> Mr. Lowman <hi>would either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the time untill</hi> Mr. Facy <hi>might be capable for ſuch a work, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire or challenge it from any other hands, it would be accepted, and either he or ſome other ſhould be appointed to meet with him, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him in his deſire or challenge. But</hi> Mr. Lowman <hi>weighing the little advantage which may redound to any by ſuch diſputes, as alſo deſiring peace, not loving diſtance or diſturbance, ſeeing</hi> Mr. Facy <hi>is for preſent diſabled, who was to meet with him, is willing alſo, the whole buſineſs may be waved and layd aſide. In token of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto this your motion, I hereto ſet my hand.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Forteſcue Lowman.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Feb. 15. 1655.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>From which at firſt ſight, things rightly conſidered, the ſerious will judge, (1.) That that fall of his which then diſabled him from being judged a ſutable diſputant with <hi>Mr. Lowman,</hi> did beforehand diſable him from ſtanding as a member in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, much more as a Paſtor in that Church. (2) And that it doth not now follow, but that the grace that hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored him to be a member, and enabled him again to improve his gift of grace to edification, may alſo ſufficiently enable him to anſwer to <hi>Mr. Lowmans</hi> deſires, if need be, and they yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main with him, to vindicate the way and practiſe that we walk in. As alſo (3.) That though <hi>Mr. Lowman</hi> was treated with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all by us, yet had he reaſons alſo of his own, leading him to a willingneſs to lay that diſputation aſide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I wiſh that the plain hearted among them, would but ſeriouſly conſider, whether they can poſſibly expect a bleſſing from heaven, under ſuch amans ministery, whoſe courſe I have a little hinted to you: and judge you, whether I have not cauſe to withdraw, where ſuch iniquity is indulged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you have his concluſion with <hi>William Facy,</hi> and now up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole of what is ſaid, either in defiance or defence of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152411:36"/>him (though we might ſay much more in the words of truth and ſoberneſs) it would appear that the man is a poor ſinner, that ſtands in dayly need of his Saviour, compaſſed about with weakneſſes, temptations, and tribulations of all kindes: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out are fightings, within are fears: whoſe footſteps are watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the iniquity of them written in his forehead, who was left for a ſeaſon under the power of the Tempter, fell in a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous manner; was ſharply rebuked of God, ſeverely cenſured by the Church, to the breaking of his bones; ſo that he hath neither the perfection of the fleſh, nor the honor of the world left him to glory in. And yet being gratiouſly delivered by Love, and upheld by Divine power from periſhing by ſin, or ſinking, is at length brought out to declare the Lords praiſe in the middeſt of his Church, who being a poor plain deſpiſed peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, abhorring the indulgence of iniquity, and not judging aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter outward appearance, but righteous judgment; finding that God hath humbled him to the duſt, remembring that they alſo themſelves are compaſſed with infirmities, and liable to be tempted; have renewed their love toward him, and can comfortably wait upon the Lord, and their waiting is not in vain in the Lord, for a bleſſing on the faithfull la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of him and others (deſpiſed) like unto him; though yet they have not clearneſs to appoint him to Paſtorſhip in a way of office, as the Accuſer falſly repeateth often as if they had done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The third particular of my charge is, for charging ſome of the</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts <hi>with denying Magiſtrates, and the neglecting of Family<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duties, and ſinging of Pſalms; let me tell you I do not charge you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a cauſe, for theſe things abound in you at that rate, that ſeeing you and ſin will not part, you and I muſt part; and though ſome of you are dear to me, whom I truſt the Lord will convince in his due time: yet the Lord Ieſus is neerer and dearer, whoſe communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I muſt, and through grace do prize before yours: had you and I continued, its to be feared, the Lord and I ſhould have parted; for while I ſat under your miniſtery, I could never find that bleſſing which I have found from that Miniſtery you deſpiſe. That tenderneſs which the Lord wrought upon my ſpirit by the publick Miniſtery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I came among you, did much decay, while I continued with you, and therefore it is no ſmall mercy, that the Lord hath brought me from you.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:152411:36"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which he calls the third particular of our Charge, for charging ſome of the Anabaptiſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was thus far worthy to be laid before him in the iniquity of it, that he had openly and very ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derouſly affirmed concerning us in the general, that we denied Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, denied family-duties, denied ſinging of Pſalms. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and on this ground had left us. The introduction to his Defence, is fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with ſuch flouriſhes and invectives, as either we meet with, and ſpeak unto elſewhere, or will be beſt anſwered by commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our Cauſe to him that judgeth righteouſly. VVe come therefore to conſider what he ſaith in the particulars, for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>For denying the power of Magiſtrates, it's notoriouſly known to many good people in</hi> Tiverton, <hi>how you have carped at the Magiſtracy there, for executing their power upon Sabbath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breakers and Quakers; yea, you confeſſed it, and pleaded it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me as many of my Friends can teſtifie, when I charged you with it, affirming, that Magiſtrates had nothing to do with Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He publickly and falſly accuſeth us, that we deny the power of Magiſtrates, or (as he alſo phraſeth it) we deny Magiſtrates: his proof is, <hi>It's notoriouſly known, we have carped at them for exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting their power on Sabbath breakers and Quakers.</hi> We have in great part declared above, and ſtill do. That we abhor the imputation of denying the power of Magiſtrates in puniſhing evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers: though withal we ſay, That it will be an hard task to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the juſtification of all the actions of perſons in Magiſtracy, who may preſume to ſmite and impriſon, in execution of paſſion and luſt, and not of Law: and that ſuch things, and ſo acted, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt Quakers, or any other People, are not onely lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but moſt abominable. As to matters relating to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and what Power the Magiſtrate may exerciſe in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, we leave the Accuſer for anſwer to the publick Edicts of the Magiſtracy it ſelf; without which, the Sect to which the Accuſer is joyned, can claim no more Priviledge in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> then any other Sect or party of People profeſſing
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152411:37"/>Religion by the Magiſtrate allowed.</p>
            <p>We utterly reject what he ſuggeſts about Sabbath-breakers, as not having the leaſt colour of Truth; of which, had there been the leaſt pretence to have faſtned it upon any, ſomewhat would have been ſaid, to tender us odious and liable to puniſhment in this Pamphlet, or at the Meeting aboveſaid, proceeding his rejection, where he was not backward to load us with whatever ignominy he could bring, to bear on us, or the way wherein we be.</p>
            <p>Touching the Quakers, what teſtimony we hold up againſt their principles is very well known to this Accuſer, and divers good people in <hi>Tiverton,</hi> and elſwere: what meaſure they have found in that town, and by whoſe violent importunity and inſtigation it hath been executed; whether to the ſatisfaction in point of conſcience of ſome that did it, or whether even conſtrained to doe it beyond a voluntary inclination; what compaſſions and complaints it occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned in many good people in that place (that are neither Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts nor Quakers) are not things unknown there. The day may ſoon enough declare it in other places, we judging it not now our work to ſay any thing unto it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>For neglecting family-duties, you cannot without bluſhing ſay that I wrong you in charging the neglect of it upon you, being conſcious to your ſelves that many of your families call not upon God, which I can confidently affirme upon my own perſonal knowledg, when I walked with you; beſides when I charged you with it, you affirmed that it was a mans liberty, not his duty to pray in his family, as my friends can teſtifie who were then preſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What his falſe accuſation about this matter was, and our defence therein, are manifeſted above, to which we refer the Reader.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>For neglecting to ſing Pſalmos, an ordinance of Chriſt, you never performed this duty in your aſſemblies: but when I charged you with this, you affirmed it to be no better then bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lads, as my friends can teſtifie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How wrongfully our denying this (as he preſented it at firſt) was
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152411:37"/>layed to our charge, may appeare by what hath been ſaid already to that point. Touching the uncomly compariſon that one of our friends it ſeems made between the tranſlation of <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalmes, by <hi>Sternhold</hi> and <hi>Hopkins,</hi> (conſidering the many additions to, and ſubſtractions from the word to make it ſpeak in rythme and meter) and the Ballads of the Book of <hi>Job;</hi> whatever might be ſayed touching the harmleſs uſe of the word heretofore, the Canti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles being in ſome ancient tranſlations of the Bible, entitled <hi>Ballad of Ballads,</hi> yet we utterly diſapprove of the expreſſion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne it, as being unſavory and offenſive: nevertheleſs herein may be obſerved the accuſers perfection in the art of ſlander, multiplying to calumaiate, ſomething will ſtick, fathering the failings of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon upon the whole party and way, whether owned by them or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned: being alſo afore-hand with invectives and falſhoods of ſuch a nature as will require time and other helps to remove; and in the interim the ſlander paſſeth for a truth, and the ſlanderer for a man that hath done notable good ſervice in making diſcoveries to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I come to the fourth and laſt particular of my charge for abuſing my father: but whether by word or deed, or in what manner, you gave me no account: but ſure I am, If I were guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſuch a thing, you never reproved me. I muſt confeſs that when I walked with you, through your inſtigation I took up many hard thoughts both of my father and mother, becauſe they laboured to convince me of mine errour, yea and I left my fathers houſe upon this very account, as I have hinted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but through mercy the Lord hath ſhewed me my evill in ſo doing, yet you were never the people that admoniſhed me all the while I walked with you. But now you act as if you would rejoyce, if you could take up any thing to reproch me, and ſet variance betwixt the father and the ſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here to avoid the ſuppoſition of his being any way guilty farther then he might father it upon the Church, he impoſeth upon the Reader theſe things:</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) That the many hard thoughts he had of his father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152411:38"/>labouring to convince him of his errour, were through this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples inſtigation.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) That upon this very account of their inſtigation, it was, that he left his fathers houſe.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) That they never reproved or admoniſhed him for any evill of this kinde.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) That we rejoyce to forge and take up any thing that may reproach him, and ſet variance betwixt the father and the ſon.</p>
            <p>That through our inſtigations he ſhould have ſuch thoughts, as it's but barely affirmed by him ſo it may ſuffice that the thing is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed and abhorred by us, as that which is beneath civility, and much more beneath Chriſtianity; that any occaſion of our inſtigation brought him to forſake his fathers houſe, is an evident falſhood, there having been former differences betwixt his father in Law (that married with his mother) and him. On a time, about his beginning to profeſs the truth we walk in, his ſaid father in law, being greatly offended with him, required him to depart from his houſe: after which paſſion was over, he deſired his father in law's leave to depart by conſent; which he obtained accordingly; whiles he walked with us, indeed his deportment to his parents, was much as he reporteth, but it is ready to be made good by many witneſſeſs, that his uncomly behaviour in this kinde, being a great grief to us, was often reproved by ſeveral, both brethren and ſiſters, as occaſion preſented. But in the caſe before us, which we had this time in charge againſt him, his revilings were of his wives father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who not complying with ſome deſires of his about his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage as he expected, reprochfully ſaid of his father in law, that he was an old knave, and that his mother in law was a ſerpent that lay in his boſom: of which being reproved by a ſiſter that heard it from him, he gave no other ſatisfaction, then this; he thought he ſhould finde them ſuch. He was afterward reproved for it by a brother, but then ſtood in the denyal of it: which being brought before the Church, with evidence of the truth thereof, they then by meſſengers did more ſolemnly exhort him to repent of ſuch ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; but he manifeſted not any, but rather a ſtubborn ſpirit. Then was both his railing and lying judged worthy with the reſt to be layd before him, if peradventure the Lord would give him repentance. Our unwillingneſs to have theſe things made publick, that he might
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152411:38"/>be brought to a ſence of his evill, without ſuch an occaſion of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord betwixt the father and the ſon, was one main reaſon, why we had a deſire to have had him apart from the multitude in the time of our proceedings with him in the Church: and it is no ſmall grief, that we are conſtrained to ſay thus much of him now; yet he hath compelled us to let all men know how far we are free from the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible things he chargeth ſo malitiouſly on us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But had I been guilty of every ſyllable of which you charge me with, how can you bring it to blaſphemy? The Truth is:</hi> Thomas Glaſs <hi>made many ſad ſhifts to mince the matter, when he was deſired to make forth, wherein I had been guilty of blaſphemy: but let all modeſt ſober Chriſtians judge, whether that which lies in the bottom be not my diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their wickedneſs, and withdrawing from them: though I could not in Conſcience continue longer with them, when God ſaid, Come out from among them; which makes them to forge ſomething againſt me; and let the Reader judge where lies the guilt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For anſwer to what he enquires about blaſphemy, he is referred to what is ſaid above: upon the whole, the modeſt ſober Chriſtian is called in by him, to give judgement: to whom alſo we gladly ſubmit the conſideration of the premiſes, Whether a perſon ſo abundantly diſcovering a raſh, perſecuting, revengeful Spirit; heaping up ſuch falſhoods and miſ-repreſentations, on the Way, on the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, on the Member whom he had forgiven, (his own neer Relations not eſcaping him) under pretecſions of a juſt Ground to leave us, were not juſtly proceeded withal; and (after all due means, found obſtinate and irreconcilable) cut off and rejected from the Congregation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus have I given you a brief Narrative of the Principles and Practices of theſe Anabaptiſts, having walked with them and tried them: and likewiſe an account of God's gracious dealing, in bringing me from them, to attend the publick Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery; and of their unjuſt proceedings againſt me in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. If the good Lord make it uſeful for the good of any poor
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152411:39"/>ſoul, to undeceive him, and bring him into the way of God, or to prevent any from departing out of God's way, I ſhall rejoyce, ſo that God may not loſe his Glory, nor any of his people loſe their comfort: which if you tender, be ſure to prize thoſe ways in which you received the firſt Conviction, leſt you one day lie down in ſorrow, for going away from God, and from the ſtriving of his Spirit. Let me ask you that have with drawn from that Miniſtery, to whom ye can ſay, We are your work of the Lord; have you the ſame tenderneſs, the ſame affections to God, that you once had in former days? are not theſe much decayed? O re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from whence you are fallen, and repent! And now I ſhall conclude, by giving the Reader an account of the ſad experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that I have had, in two yeers digreſſion from the publick Miniſtery in</hi> Tiverton, <hi>which God did at firſt bloſs to the awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of my ſoul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As he draws towards his Concluſion, you have the Application of his miſerable Doctrines after he hath, with ſome flattering inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, beſpoke the farther attention of his ignorant young Chriſtian (as he calls him in his Title-page) That now he may give a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of his fixed enmity to the way he was in, and ſhew far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what Oracle he hath conſulted with, and what Spirit he is of; he adventures on the houſe top, in the ſight of the Sun (under the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts of his two yeers ſad experience) to caſt upon the way of the Lord, and them that walk therein, ſuch horrible reproaches, as the thoughts of Temperance, Righteouſneſs, and Judgement to come, would have made him tremble at; having, though ſeemingly, aimed at them in <hi>Tiverton</hi> therein, yet ſo ſhot, as may indifferently reach all them anywhere that ſerve the Lord Jeſus Chriſt under that name of reproach.</p>
            <p>Under all which, as a part of our Crown, we could quietly ſit down, and pray, <hi>Lord lay it not to his charge: Father, forgive him, he knoweth not what he doth:</hi> appealing for our Vindication to the Conſciences of all ſerious, unbyaſſed, and unprejudiced Chriſtians, that have taſted our Doctrine, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved our walkings in the three Nations, whether the things be ſo, or nay; and ſo leave it to the God and Father of the Spirits of all fleſh, who is coming out to paſs righteous judgement in all ſuch
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152411:39"/>caſes for his poor people that wait for him. But yet for their ſakes at whom he levels, who being ignorant of us, may be apt to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at ſuch an impudent teſtimony; we preſent a few animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions on the two or three firſt things he ſaith; the reſt being ſuch wretched falſhoods as we abhor the thoughts of; and delivered in ſuch general termes, without any particular inſtance, wherein it is poſſible to trace him, we reckon not worthy any other anſwer then that, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120.2, 3, 4. and 52.1, — 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>I do not remember that I have had one conviction, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all the ſermons which I heard whileſt I walked among them; but that ſence of my condition which I had before, did abate, and by little and little fall away, after I turned my back upon the means, which God made uſe of in working upon me. Therefore I beg all thoſe upon whoſe hearts God is working, to take heed of deſpiſing, or ſlighting thoſe inſtruments with whom God is preſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reader muſt ſuppoſe his meaning to be either, that he felt no ſuch thing as motions, quicknings, ſoule-ſearchings, &amp;c. while with us; or elſe, that whatever of that kinde he had, they are now to be accounted no other then deluſions; and ſo not worthy the name of convictions, or of being remembred. If the former be imagined to be his meaning, we have abundant and pregnant teſtimonies, how that many times he hath declared his having met with God to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, while he hath with us been waiting on him; ſo that he would not have given ſuch opportunities (as he hath reported) for the world. But if he mindes all theſe to have been the deluſions of his own heart, we ſhall not contend about it; but that likely they were ſo, or that he diſſembled thoſe pretenſions of enjoying God. Only it further ſhewes the mercy we have, of being delivered from ſuch a deceitful m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mber, who either then belyed the ſpirit, while he owned ſuch operations to him, as were none of his; or if they were the ſpirits works doth now in effect deny them. Nay, the miſtake is very great, if it cannot be made good that he being (ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the publiſhing of this pamphlet in his name) demanded by a member, how he could date affirm ſuch a thing, that he had no
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152411:40"/>convictions, &amp;c. replyed, that he never had ſayd ſuch a thing. If ſo, the Reader may gueſs what hand it's likely himſelf had in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piling the book; which with other evidences, if we liked to produce them, would put that matter out of queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>I was drawn off by theſe men, when I was in the greateſt probability of receiving good from the miniſtry that I ever was: for I doe remember ſtill the impreſſions which were made upon my ſoule by thoſe truths, which I heard from</hi> Mr. Chiſhul, <hi>a little before I was thus drawn aſide, which did work mightily to conviction and to reſolution in me: but the devill envying my proſperity, ſent me this thorne in the fleſh; and their inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and temptations did ſo prevaile with me that I left this miniſtry to attend on them, which was but a diverſion from the work of my ſoule: and I finde that whereas before I had ſome things of weight upon my ſpirit, theſe were ſoon layed aſide, and I had nothing to doe but to diſpute about Baptiſme, and to raile againſt miniſters, ſo that my former awakenings were turned into drouſineſs and doting about queſtions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How unskilful this man is of judging about Convictions, appears in part by what is laſt ſaid; How infaithful he is in reporting them; is no leſs evident by conſidering, that when he came at firſt to make out among us a profeſſion of his faith in order to fellowſhip with us, he teſtified, that the firſt convictions that were wrought on his ſoule, were through the word of the Lord held forth in the Church, after which (as himſelf ſaid) for worldly reſpects, he went again to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend on the publick miniſtry; but was there met with, by ſome word of <hi>Mr. Chiſhul,</hi> which put life again into his former convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions begotten by the miniſtry with us: whereupon he returned again, and on a declaration of the work of faith was baptiſed and admitted. If this teſtimony of his was in truth, and a true work of grace was on him, then did the Lord witneſs to our miniſtry; if he deceived us in that profeſſion, then hath the Lord witneſſed to our rejecting him; <hi>he went out from us, becauſe he was not of us.</hi> Whereas he lays the ſtreſs of his coming to us, upon our inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating and tempting him, after the ſtricteſt ſearch, it doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that any were urgent with him at all, but that of his own
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152411:40"/>voluntary inclinatition he propoſed his deſires of communion firſt to a particular member (now with the Lord) and then unto the whole.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>As I found no profit my ſelf by attending on their teaching, ſo I obſerved little to any other. Nay, it hath been not only mine, but the experience of others, who have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly attended them as long as my ſelf, that there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but deadneſs of ſpirit to be gained there, which hath at laſt cauſed them to deſert them alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Accuſer doth not tell you, that thoſe conſtant attenders that have deſerted us were members with us (there being but his wiſe and one or two more ſince, that on that pretenſion have left that Church) as for uſual hearers, if any of them are gone on this ground, as it's more then they have declared, ſo neither is it viſible by any loſs of number in that great concourſe. But put caſe that (we lying under ſo great reproach as the Accuſer hath pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly and doeth dayly wait and labour with his new friends to caſt upon us) both Members of the Church and Attenders on it ſhould be offended, finding fault with Miniſters, Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp;c. would this become a convincing Argument with a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious heart, that God is witneſſing againſt the way? hath it not been the common tryal of Gods own people heretofore? and at this day is there not to be obſerved and lamented, a ſpirit of giddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs taking great hold of men and things; ſo that the whole ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of what of late dayes had on it the impreſſion of Reformation, ſeeming as it were to labour and encline towards its ancient cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption? In which houſe of temptation we are indeed in expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of greater tryals then theſe, and yet in the middeſt of them have this to be glad in our God for, that all along he hath not left us without ſeveral gratious teſtimonies of his converting and quickning preſence, notwithſtanding our Accuſer, and ſuch ſpirits as his is, may have taſted little of it, but have been filled with their own wayes.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:152411:41"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Accuſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>They are very vigilant and watchful to finde out any that are convinced and awakened under the publick miniſtry: and when they begin to ſee things a little darkly and confuſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they take the advantage of this twilight, in which their ſoules are to put off their commadities: where their ſoules have ſome tenderneſs and yet a great deal of ignorance they are fit to wrought upon by them; for by reaſon of the firſt, they dare not neglect a command of God; and by reaſon of the ſecond, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares to them that it is neceſſary to be dipt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This fourth Experiment comes to appearance very big into the world, and promiſing great diſcoveries, ſuddenly eaſeth it ſelf of ſix monſtrous births, conceived in the wombe of it: all which, for the ſubſtance of them, are no other then the old pulpit and preſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worne-ſlanders that the dragon hath had ready in all generations as a flood to poure out upon the Lords people, who have labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed faithfully to beare their teſtimony and ſet their ſhoulders to the work of reformation, or to the recovery of any truth in Doctrine or practiſe from the pollutions of the man of ſinne, againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and ſtreame of the fleſhly wiſdome and glory of the times they have lived in. All which, as we might caſt off at once, by teſtifying an holy deteſtation through grace in our hearts againſt the baſeneſs of the things ſuggeſted; ſo need we, and ſhall we, ſay the leſs to them.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) For that there are no particular perſons inſtanced, who in the things layd to our charge may be made out demonſtrably to be guilty; and it is our comfortable aſſurance, that on a faithful and impartial ſearch they will not be found; but that the ſlander will return on the Accuſers head, and none be ſtumbled at it; unleſs ſuch as may judge, that this Accuſers truth and faithfulneſs in this narrative examined, deſerves for him that he be believed in a matter of this moment upon his own word.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) In that our Accuſer with his own pen freeth thoſe that are Godly among us from theſe things, ſaying toward the cloſe [<hi>I ſpeake
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152411:41"/>not this of all: for as I have ſaid, I believe there is a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of godly among them,</hi> &amp;c.] our intereſt is not, (our cauſe needs not) that we ſhould plead for any ungodly ones, or any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly deeds that they ſhall commit if any ſuch ſhall be found guilty of the things charged, and perſiſt in them, let them beare their judgment whoever they be: the Lord will we hope in due time diſcover them, and deliver us from them.</p>
            <p>For what is ſaid of our inſinuations on the ignorant with preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of love from us or peace from God, preſſing them ſpeedily to Baptiſme, and having all our zeale for the practiſe of holineſs running into that; we abhor and reject as baſe falſhoods, as might appeare from our not accepting the tenders of many perſons deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring baptiſme and communion with us, when we cannot be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in ſome good meaſure of illumination in their underſtanding, and diſtinct knowledge of the work of converſion on their hearts; though we judge it our duty to be tender to the babes in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Touching our own ignorance, with which we are often bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by this our Accuſer, and our ſhunning the light; its true we are reputed, and know our ſelves to be a weak and darke people; yet we declare, that through the ſupporting mercy of God, whom we fear, and on whom in this day of rebuke and blaſphemy, we rely for help, we ſhall not ceaſe to witneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>before great and ſmall, as the Lord ſhall miniſter ability, and clear up our way,</p>
            <p>That the doctrine which we profeſs, and particularly that point of baptiſing only upon perſonal profeſſion of ſaving faith, is a doctrine according to Godlineſs, and the ſame which was once delivered to the Saints (excepting nevertheleſs to our ſelves, and owning whatever miſcarriages through perſonall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, may accompany this profeſſion of truth in this day of ſmall things.) Neither ſhall we ſhun to teſtifie, that the impoſing of the fleſhly off ſpring upon the Goſpel-Church, is a doctrine without Scripture, foundation. And we doe teſtifie, that in this faith we ſtand through grace, and have peace with God in it; withall, we deſire the upright in heart to weigh and conſider
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:152411:42"/>faithfully as for God, how much the ſaid doctrine impoſing the fleſhly off-ſpring on the Goſpel Church ſperplexeth and obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the light, and order of the miniſtration of the everlaſting covenant eſtabliſhed by the Son of God: how it confoundeth the main diſtinction of the two Convenants in the different principle of their reſpective ſubjects, typified by <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 21.10. and explained <hi>Gal</hi> 4.22-30. &amp; <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.8. diſtinguiſhed in plain terms by the children of the fleſh, and the children of promiſe, with reſpect to the ſeveral ſeaſons of Law and Goſpel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13, 14. How it alſo darkneth the honor and dignity which the Goſpel. Miniſtration exalteth the Jew and his poſterity unto, by confirming unto them the firſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of divine Grace by a ſpecial inſtitution of this Miniſtration, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.5, 6. whereby from their former priviledge of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants under the bondage-convenant, they by faith in the grace ſo tendred to them, obtain for ever the priviledge and dignity of Sons and heirs of God, a more noble deſcent then that of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither can that ſuggeſtion, <hi>[That baptizing only upon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall profeſſion is a narrowing of the Covenant of grace]</hi> be of any weight, ſeeing no ſubject which the Covenant of grace, either in the nature or preſent exhibition thereof, declareth and judgeth competent in any degree, ſtands excluded by it, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we be thereof judged, becauſe we dare not preſume in point of practiſe in inſtituted worſhip, to depart from a plaine known rule, to follow uncertain ſuppoſitions. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding alſo our Accuſer be among others come forth to mock and reproach us for it; a man that hath been our companion in the counſels of the houſe of God: and as <hi>David</hi> found that an ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation to his afflictions, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41.9. <hi>and</hi> 55.12, 13, 14. ſo is it with us this day in behalf of this poor man, who may doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs become a ſtumbling ſtone to credulous &amp; incantious ſouls; but we are taught to caſt our care in ſuch a caſe upon God, ſeeing the caſe is particularly his to provide for; and we are perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that though thouſands ſhould fall off, &amp; be offended in this day of manifold temptations, through worldly diſadvantages, yet that thereby the truth wherein we ſtand, ſhould only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive purgation from the blemiſhes that are brought upon it by
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
